<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poems and discourses occasionally written by John Norris ...</title>
            <author>Norris, John, 1657-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27458</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11851102</idno>
  <idno type="VID">49931</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248517723</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16138</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11851102</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49931)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 544:10a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Poems and discourses occasionally written by John Norris ...</title>
                  <author>Norris, John, 1657-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Harefinch for James Norris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>With: An idea of happiness in a letter to a friend / John Norris. The second edition. London : Printed for James Norris ..., 1684.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">English poetry --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:1"/>
                  <p>POEMS AND DISCOURSES Occasionally Written</p>
                  <p>By <hi>John Norris,</hi> Fellow of <hi>All-Souls-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Nec vos dulcissima Mundi</l>
                     <l>Nomina, vos Musae, libertas, otia, libri,</l>
                     <l>Vos Horti Sylvaeque anima remanente relinquam.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Harefinch,</hi> for <hi>James Norris,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> MDCLXXXIV.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:2"/>
                  <head>To the excellently accomplish'd Lady, Madam <hi>Anne Strick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Daughter to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sir <hi>Thomas Strickland,</hi> of <hi>Boynton</hi> in <hi>York</hi>-shire, Baronet.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I</hi> Could have satisfy'd my self with the <hi>humble</hi> Content of a lower <hi>Patronage,</hi> were I not more ambitious of giving some Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of that great Service which I owe You, than of deriving Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon my self from the <hi>glory</hi> of your <hi>Protection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But tho Ambition be not my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Aim, yet I find that the greatness of your Quality and the
<pb facs="tcp:49931:3"/>excellency of your Personal Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishments will render it suspicious that in this Dedication I rather intend <hi>Honour</hi> to my <hi>self,</hi> than <hi>Service</hi> to <hi>You,</hi> so that my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion will appear doubtful and obscure, and my <hi>Incense,</hi> in too lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral a sense, <hi>ascend</hi> in a <hi>Cloud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, <hi>Madam,</hi> let not the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> necessity which I lye under of advantaging my own Credit while I serve you, prejudice the sincerity of my Intentions, or make my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiousness to be thought <hi>Mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> 'Tis the constant Fate of all the Votaries of <hi>Greatness</hi> to be engaged in such a Necessity, and it happens to be so as well in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49931:3"/>as in <hi>Civil</hi> Address. Thus the Altar, which is intended mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for an Instrument of Devotion and Religious Service, is it self made aweful and Sacred by the <hi>Inscription</hi> which it wears, and becomes honourable by the <hi>Livery</hi> of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Madam,</hi> I wish you could find as many things in this Oblation which would <hi>deserve</hi> your Patron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, as you will that will <hi>need</hi> it. However, I hope your <hi>goodness</hi> will <hi>pardon</hi> what your <hi>Judgment</hi> cannot <hi>approve.</hi> Here is one <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> which has had the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> to please so well, that tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to make a second Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb facs="tcp:49931:4"/>upon the Stage. Whether the rest are born under the same <hi>lucky Planet</hi> I know not; but your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance (Madam) will <hi>calculate</hi> their <hi>Nativity,</hi> for thence I shall take the measures of my Success. I value your single approbation more than the <hi>Applause</hi> of a <hi>Theatre,</hi> but if I miss of both, yet I hope you will give me leave to promise my self a Pardon for the Presumption of this Address, and to assume to my self the <hi>Honourable</hi> Title of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>(Madam)</salute>
                     <signed>Your most humble and devoted Servant <hi>J. N.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49931:4"/>
                  <head>The Passion of our B. Saviour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented in a Pindarique Ode.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <l>—Quis talia fando</l>
                        <l>Temperet a Lacrymis?—</l>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>SAY <hi>bold Licentious</hi> Muse,</l>
                     <l>What <hi>Noble</hi> Subject wilt thou chuse,</l>
                     <l>Of what great <hi>Hero,</hi> of what <hi>mighty</hi> thing,</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou in <hi>boundless</hi> numbers sing?</l>
                     <l>Sing the <hi>unfathom'd</hi> Depths of <hi>Love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(For who the Wonders done by <hi>Love</hi> can tell,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Love,</hi> which is it self <hi>all Miracle?</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Here in vast endless Circles may'st thou rove,</l>
                     <l>And like the travelling Planet of the day</l>
                     <l>In an Orb <hi>unbounded</hi> stray.</l>
                     <l>Sing the great Miracle of Love <hi>Divine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Great be thy <hi>Genius, sparkling</hi> every Line,</l>
                     <l>Love's greatest <hi>Mystery</hi> reherse,</l>
                     <l>Greater then that</l>
                     <l>Which on the teeming <hi>Chaos</hi> brooding sate,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>hatch'd,</hi> with kindly heat, the Universe.</l>
                     <l>How <hi>God</hi> in Mercy chose to <hi>bleed,</hi> and <hi>dye</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To rescue <hi>Man</hi> from Misery,</l>
                     <l>Man, not his <hi>Creature</hi> only, but his <hi>Enemy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49931:5"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Lo, in <hi>Gethsemane,</hi> I see him prostrate lye,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Press'd</hi> with the <hi>weight</hi> of his great Agony.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>common</hi> Sluces of the Eyes</l>
                     <l>To vent his <hi>mighty</hi> Passion won't suffice,</l>
                     <l>His tortured Body weeps <hi>all-o're,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And out of every Pore</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Buds</hi> forth a <hi>pretious</hi> Gem of Purple Gore.</l>
                     <l>How strange the Power of afflictions rod</l>
                     <l>When in the Hand of an incensed God!</l>
                     <l>Like the <hi>commanding</hi> Wand</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Moses</hi> Hand</l>
                     <l>It works a Miracle, and turns the <hi>Flood</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Tears</hi> into a <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Blood.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>See with what <hi>Pomp</hi> Sorrow does now appear!</l>
                     <l>How <hi>proud</hi> She is of being seated here!</l>
                     <l>She never wore</l>
                     <l>So <hi>rich</hi> a <hi>Dye</hi> before.</l>
                     <l>Long was he willing to decline</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Encounter</hi> of the Wrath Divine.</l>
                     <l>Thrice he sent for his Release</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pathetic Embassies</hi> of Peace,</l>
                     <l>At length his Courage overcame his Doubt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Resolv'd</hi> he was, and so the <hi>bloody Flagg</hi> hung out.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>And now the <hi>Tragic Scene</hi>'s displai'd,</l>
                     <l>Where drawn in full <hi>Battalia</hi> are laid</l>
                     <l>Before his Eyes</l>
                     <l>That numerous <hi>Host</hi> of Miseries</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49931:5"/>
                     <l>He must withstand, that <hi>Map</hi> of Woe</l>
                     <l>Which he must undergo.</l>
                     <l>That heavy <hi>Wine-press</hi> which must by him be <hi>trod,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The whole <hi>Artillery</hi> of God.</l>
                     <l>He saw that Face whose very Sight</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chears</hi> Angels with its <hi>Beatific</hi> Light,</l>
                     <l>Contracted now into a dreadful frown,</l>
                     <l>All <hi>cloath'd</hi> with Thunder, <hi>big</hi> with death</l>
                     <l>And Showers of hot burning Wrath,</l>
                     <l>Which shortly must be poured down.</l>
                     <l>He saw a black and dismal Scroll</l>
                     <l>Of Sins past, present, and to come,</l>
                     <l>With their intolerable Doom</l>
                     <l>Which would the more oppress his <hi>spotless</hi> Soul;</l>
                     <l>As th' Elements are weighty proved</l>
                     <l>When from their <hi>Native</hi> Station they'r removed.</l>
                     <l>He saw the foul <hi>Ingratitude</hi> of those</l>
                     <l>Who would the <hi>Labours</hi> of his Love oppose,</l>
                     <l>And reap no benefit by all his <hi>Agonys.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He saw all this,</l>
                     <l>And as he saw to <hi>Waver</hi> he began,</l>
                     <l>And almost to <hi>repent</hi> of his great Love for Man.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>When lo, a heavenly Form all bright and fair,</l>
                     <l>Swister then <hi>Thought</hi> shot through th' <hi>enlight'ned</hi> Air.</l>
                     <l>He who sat next th' <hi>imperial</hi> Throne,</l>
                     <l>And read the Councels of the Great <hi>Three-One,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who in Eternity's <hi>Misterious Glass</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Saw both what was, what is, and what must come to pass;</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49931:6"/>
                     <l>He came with Reverence profound,</l>
                     <l>And rais'd his <hi>prostrate Maker</hi> from the Ground;</l>
                     <l>Wiped off the bloody Sweat</l>
                     <l>With which his <hi>Face</hi> and <hi>Garments</hi> too were wet,</l>
                     <l>And comforted his dark <hi>benighted</hi> Mind</l>
                     <l>With sovereign Cordials of <hi>Light refin'd.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This done, in soft addresses he began</l>
                     <l>To <hi>fortifie</hi> his kind Designs for Man,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ʋnseal'd</hi> to him the Book of Gods Decree:</l>
                     <l>And shew'd him what <hi>must</hi> be,</l>
                     <l>Alledg'd the Truth of <hi>Prophecies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Types, Figures,</hi> and <hi>Mysteries,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>How needful it was to supply</l>
                     <l>With humane Race the <hi>ruins</hi> of the Skie.</l>
                     <l>How this would <hi>new accession</hi> bring</l>
                     <l>To the <hi>Coelestial Quire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And how withall it would inspire</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>New Matter</hi> for the Praise of the great King.</l>
                     <l>How he should see the <hi>travail of his Soul,</hi> and bless</l>
                     <l>Those Sufferings which had so good Success.</l>
                     <l>How great the <hi>Triumphs</hi> of his Victory,</l>
                     <l>How glorious his <hi>Ascent</hi> would be,</l>
                     <l>What <hi>weighty</hi> Bliss in Heaven he should obtain</l>
                     <l>By a few Hours of Pain,</l>
                     <l>Where to <hi>Eternal</hi> Ages he should Reign.</l>
                     <l>He spake, confirm'd in mind the <hi>Champion</hi> stood,</l>
                     <l>A Spirit divine</l>
                     <l>Through the thick <hi>Veil</hi> of Flesh did shine,</l>
                     <l>All over <hi>Powerful</hi> he was, all over <hi>Good.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49931:6"/>
                     <l>Pleas'd with his successful Flight,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Officious</hi> Angel posts away</l>
                     <l>To the bright Regions of Eternal Day,</l>
                     <l>Departing in a <hi>track</hi> of <hi>Light.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In haste for News the heavenly People ran,</l>
                     <l>And joy'd to hear the <hi>hopeful</hi> State of Man.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <l>And now that strange prodigious hour,</l>
                     <l>When God must subject be to humane Power,</l>
                     <l>That Hour is come,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>unetring Clock</hi> of <hi>Fate</hi> has <hi>struck,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Twas heard below down to Hell's <hi>lowest</hi> Room,</l>
                     <l>And strait th'Infernal Powers th' <hi>appointed signal</hi> took.</l>
                     <l>Open the <hi>Scene</hi> my Muse, and see</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wonders</hi> of Impudence and Villany;</l>
                     <l>How wicked <hi>Mercenary</hi> hands</l>
                     <l>Dare to <hi>invade</hi> him whom they should <hi>adore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With Swords &amp; Staves incompass'd round he stands,</l>
                     <l>Who knew no other <hi>Guards</hi> but those of Heaven before.</l>
                     <l>Once with his <hi>powerful</hi> breath he did repell</l>
                     <l>The rude assaults of Hell.</l>
                     <l>A ray of his <hi>Divinity</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shot forth with that bold Answer, <hi>I am He,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They <hi>reel</hi> and <hi>stagger,</hi> and <hi>fall</hi> to the Ground,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>God</hi> was in the Sound.</l>
                     <l>The Voice of God was once again</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Walking</hi> in the <hi>Garden</hi> heard,</l>
                     <l>And once again was by the <hi>guilty</hi> Hearers fear'd;</l>
                     <l>Trembling seiz'd every joynt, and chilness every Vein.</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49931:7"/>
                     <l>This <hi>little</hi> Victory he won,</l>
                     <l>Shew'd what he <hi>could</hi> have done.</l>
                     <l>But he to whom as <hi>chief</hi> was given</l>
                     <l>The whole <hi>Militia</hi> of Heaven,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Mighty</hi> He</l>
                     <l>Declines all Guards for his defence</l>
                     <l>But that of his <hi>inseparable Incocence;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>quietly</hi> gives up his Liberty.</l>
                     <l>He's seiz'd on by the <hi>Military bands,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With Cords they bind his <hi>sacred</hi> hands,</l>
                     <l>But ah! how <hi>weak,</hi> what <hi>nothings</hi> would they prove,</l>
                     <l>Were he not held by <hi>stronger</hi> ones of <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <l>Once more, my weary'd Muse, thy Pinions try,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>reach</hi> the top of <hi>Calvary.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>steep Ascent:</hi> But most to him who bore</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Burthen</hi> of a <hi>Cross</hi> this way before.</l>
                     <l>(The Cross <hi>ascends,</hi> there's something in it sure</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Moral</hi> is and <hi>mystical,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No <hi>Heights</hi> of Fortune are from thee secure,</l>
                     <l>Afflictions sometimes <hi>Climb,</hi> as well as <hi>fall</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Here breath a while, and view</l>
                     <l>The dolefull'st <hi>Picture</hi> Sorrow ever <hi>drew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Lord of Life,</hi> Heavens <hi>darling</hi> Son,</l>
                     <l>The Great, th' Almighty one,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>out-stretch'd</hi> Arms, nail'd to a <hi>cursed</hi> Tree,</l>
                     <l>Crown'd with sharp Thorns, cover'd with Infamy;</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49931:7"/>
                     <l>He who before</l>
                     <l>So many <hi>Miracles</hi> had done,</l>
                     <l>The Lives of <hi>others</hi> to <hi>restore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Does with a <hi>greater, lose</hi> his <hi>own.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Full three long hours his <hi>tender</hi> body did sustain</l>
                     <l>Most exquisite and <hi>poignant</hi> pain.</l>
                     <l>So long the <hi>Sympathizing</hi> Sun his light <hi>withdrew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>wonder'd</hi> how the <hi>Stars</hi> their <hi>dying</hi> Lord could.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <l>This strange defect of light</l>
                     <l>Does all the <hi>Sages</hi> in <hi>Astronomy</hi> affright</l>
                     <l>With fears of an <hi>Eternal</hi> Night.</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Intelligences</hi> in their Courses <hi>stray,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Travellers</hi> below <hi>mistake</hi> their way,</l>
                     <l>Wond'ring to be <hi>benighted</hi> in the midst of <hi>Day.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Each mind is seiz'd with <hi>Horror</hi> and <hi>Despair,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And more <hi>o're-spread</hi> with <hi>darkness</hi> than the <hi>air.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fear on, 'tis <hi>wondrous</hi> all and <hi>new,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis what past Ages never knew.</l>
                     <l>Fear on, but yet you'll find</l>
                     <l>The <hi>great Eclipse</hi> is still behind.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>lustre</hi> of the face <hi>Divine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Does on the <hi>Mighty Sufferer</hi> no longer <hi>shine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>God hides his Glories from his sight</l>
                     <l>With a thick <hi>Skreen</hi> made of Hell's <hi>grossest</hi> night.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Close-wrought</hi> it was, and <hi>Solid</hi> all,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Compacted</hi> and <hi>Substantial,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Impenetrable</hi> to the <hi>Beatifick</hi> light</l>
                     <l>Without <hi>Complaint</hi> he bore</l>
                     <l>The tortures he endur'd <hi>before;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49931:8"/>
                     <l>But <hi>now</hi> no longer able to <hi>contain</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Under the great <hi>Hyperbole</hi> of pain,</l>
                     <l>He <hi>mourns,</hi> and with a strong <hi>Pathetick</hi> cry,</l>
                     <l>Laments the sad <hi>Desertion</hi> of the <hi>Diety.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here stop my Muse, stop and admire,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Breather</hi> of all Life does now <hi>expire;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His <hi>Milder</hi> Father Summons him away,</l>
                     <l>His Breath <hi>obediently</hi> he does resign;</l>
                     <l>Angels to <hi>Paradice</hi> his Soul convey,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Calm</hi> the <hi>Relicts</hi> of his grief with <hi>Hymns</hi> divine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="commentary_on_poem">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49931:8"/>
                     <head>Annotations.</head>
                     <p>THis Ode (if I mistake not) carries all throughout the true <hi>Genius</hi> and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Pindarique</hi> Poetry; which is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est and most magnificent kind of writing in Verse, and consequently fit only for great and noble Subjects, such as are as <hi>boundless</hi> as its <hi>own Numbers:</hi> The nature of which is to be loose and free, and not to keep one settled pace, but sometimes like a gentle stream to glide along peaceably within its own Channel, and sometimes, like an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous Torrent, to <hi>roul</hi> on extravagantly, and carry all before it. Agreeable to that description of <hi>Horace:</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>Nunc pace delabentis Hetruscum</l>
                           <l>In mare, nunc lapides adesos</l>
                           <l>Stirpesque raptas &amp; pecus &amp; domos</l>
                           <l>Volventis una non sine montium,</l>
                           <l>Clamore vincinaeque Sylvae.</l>
                        </q> And this may serve to explain the Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Poem:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49931:9"/>
                        <q>And hatch'd with kindly heat the Ʋniverse.</q> Love in the <hi>Gentile Theology,</hi> is made the most ancient of the Gods, and the Sire of all things. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, says <hi>Plutarch.</hi> And it is described by <hi>Simmias Rhodius,</hi> in a pair of Wings, which suited well with the <hi>Symbolical</hi> representation of the <hi>Chaos</hi> by an Egg, which was brooded and hatch'd under these Wings of Love. This whole matter is rarely well, and at large express'd by <hi>Aristophanes</hi> in <hi>Avibus.</hi> The plain and <hi>undisguised</hi> meaning of it is this, That the Creation of the World was the effect of the Divine Love, God having no other end in it besides the <hi>Communication</hi> of his own <hi>Happiness.</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>As th' Elements are weighty proved,</l>
                           <l>When from their Native Station they're removed.</l>
                        </q> This is according to the <hi>Aristotelean Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,</hi> that the Elements are not heavy in their own places, which whether it be true or no, I shall not now dispute. However, it serves for an <hi>Illustration,</hi> which is sufficient for my present purpose.</p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49931:9"/>
                     <q>He saw the foul Ingratitude of those, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>The bitter Ingredients of our Lord's Cup mention'd hitherto, were taken from things relating to his own <hi>personal</hi> concern. But this last motive of his Sorrow proceeds whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the behalf of <hi>others,</hi> of whose final im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitence he is suppos'd to have a foresight. This I take to be a good and proper insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the excellency of our Blessed Lord's temper, his exceeding great Love and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthropy,</hi> when among the other Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of his Passion this is supposed to be one, that there would be some, who, by their own default, would receive no benefit from it.
<q>Ʋnseal'd to him the Book of God's decree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q> Whether the Angel used these <hi>topicks</hi> of Consolation or no, is a thing as indifferent to my purpose, as 'tis <hi>uncertain.</hi> In the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it is only said in general, that <hi>there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd an Angel from Heaven strengthning him.</hi> However, these Arguments are such as are probable and pertinent, and that's suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49931:10"/>
                        <q>
                           <l>In haste for news the heavenly people ran,</l>
                           <l>And joy'd to hear the hopeful state of man.</l>
                        </q> It is highly reasonable to believe that those blessed and excellent Spirits, who out of their compassionate love and concern for mankind, usher'd in the news of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Nativity with <hi>Anthems</hi> of <hi>Praise</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving;</hi> and are said likewise to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice</hi> at the Conversion of a Sinner, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so mightily transported with joy, when they understood that our Saviour, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>reluctancy</hi> of <hi>innocent</hi> Nature, was at length fully resolv'd to undertake the <hi>Price</hi> of our Redemption.
<q>
                           <l>Full three long hours his Tender Body did sustain</l>
                           <l>Most exquisite and poignant pain.</l>
                        </q> It is supposed by the Ancient Fathers, that the Sufferings which our B. Saviour underwent in his Body, were more afflictive to him than the same would have been to another man, upon the account of the excellency and quickness of his sense of feeling: And this opinion I take to be as <hi>reasonable,</hi> as 'tis <hi>pious.</hi> For since, according to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Philosophy, the sense of feeling arises
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49931:10"/>from the proportion of the first Qualities, it follows, that the better the complexion or temperament of any man is, the better his Feeling must needs be. Now 'tis very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable to believe, that that man who was to be substantially united to the <hi>God-head,</hi> and who was begotten by the miraculous <hi>overshadowings</hi> of the holy Spirit, should have a Body endow'd with the best Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, and most noble <hi>Harmony</hi> of Qualities that could be, that so it might be a suitable Organ for his excellent Soul. And if so, then it follows that the flesh of our Lord's Body was so soft and tender, and his feeling so exquisitely quick and sensible, as never any man's was before: And consequently the severe usages which he underwent, not only at his <hi>Passion,</hi> but throughout his <hi>whole</hi> Life, must needs be in a <hi>Singular</hi> manner af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictive to him. And hence appears the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of their opinion, who are little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing affected with the consideration of our Lords Passion, because they think it was made light to him, by reason of his union with the <hi>God-head.</hi> 'Twas easie for him (some inconsiderate Persons are ready to say) to suffer this or this, for he was God, and not meer man, as we are. True, he was so,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49931:11"/>but his being God did no way lessen the punishment he underwent as <hi>man,</hi> but only supported him in his <hi>existence</hi> under it, in the same manner as God is supposed, by an act of his Almighty Power, to preserve the bodies of the <hi>Damn'd, incorruptible</hi> among the <hi>everlasting burnings.</hi> But this I think is no <hi>kindness</hi> to them. Neither did the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Divine Nature any more dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the Sufferings of our dearest Lord; nay, in one respect it proved an <hi>accidental aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> to them, because upon the account of this Noble Union he had given him a Body of a most admirable Complexion and Harmonious Temperature, and consequently of a Flesh exceeding tender, and most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitely perceptive of the least impressions.
<q>
                           <l>So long the Sympathizing Sun his light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</l>
                           <l>And wonder'd how the Stars their dying Lord could view.</l>
                        </q> The <hi>Eclipse</hi> which accompany'd the Passion of our Saviour was so remarkable and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, that 'twas taken notice of by many of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Historians: And moreover, <hi>Dionysius Areopagita,</hi> then a Professor of Philosophy at <hi>Heliopolis</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> affirms in an Epistle to <hi>Policarp,</hi> that he, with <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49931:11"/>another Philosopher of great note, saw it, and consider'd it with a great deal of admiration. There are three things which made this Eclipse so very remarkable, the time of its <hi>Appearance,</hi> the time of its <hi>Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the <hi>Degree</hi> of it. 1. For the time of its Appearance, it was at <hi>full Moon,</hi> when the Moon was not in <hi>Conjunction</hi> with, but in opposition to the Sun. And this appears not only from the testimony of <hi>Dionysius,</hi> who affirms that he saw it at that time, but also from the time of our Lord's <hi>Passion,</hi> which, according to the relation of the <hi>Evangelist,</hi> was at the Celebration of the <hi>Passeover.</hi> Now the <hi>Jews</hi> were bound to celebrate the <hi>Paschal</hi> Solemnity always at full Moon, as is to be seen in the twelfth of <hi>Exodus.</hi> This was no time therefore for a <hi>Natural</hi> Eclipse, because 'twas impossible that the Moon should then interpose betwixt us and the Sun. 2. For the time of its <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> it was full three hours, which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evidence that this was no <hi>Natural</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipse: For the <hi>Natural</hi> Eclipse of the Sun can never last so long, both because of the great disproportion between the Suns Magnitude, and that of the Moon, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the swift motion of the <hi>latter.</hi>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49931:12"/>3. For the <hi>degree</hi> of it, it was a <hi>total</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipse. The Sun was so darkned, that (as Historians report, who write of that Eclipse) the <hi>Stars</hi> appear'd. And this is another Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that it was no <hi>Natural Phoenomenon,</hi> it being impossible that the Body of the Moon, which is so infinitely less than that of the Sun, should <hi>totally</hi> eclipse it. Now all these three Remarkables are comprized in the compass of these two Verses. For in that it is said that the <hi>Sun withdrew his light,</hi> it is intimated that the light of the Sun was not <hi>intercepted</hi> by the ordinary <hi>conjunction</hi> of the Moon, but that by an Extraordinary <hi>Commission</hi> from the God of Nature, the Sun <hi>rein'd</hi> in his light, and <hi>suspended</hi> the emissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Beams. And this denotes the time of its <hi>appearance, (viz.)</hi> when the Moon was not in <hi>Conjunction.</hi> The time of its <hi>duration</hi> is implied by the words, <hi>So long.</hi> And lastly, the <hi>Degree</hi> of it is implied in the last Verse,
<q>And wonder'd how the Stars their dying Lord could view.</q> Where the appearance of the Stars is not <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly</hi> express'd, but only <hi>insinuated</hi> and <hi>couch'd,</hi> for the more elegancy of the thought.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49931:12"/>
                        <q>And calm the Relicts of his grief with Hymns divine.</q> It is here supposed that the Passion of our Saviour was now over, and his Father's wrath wholly appeas'd. For I can by no means approve the opinion of those who fancy that our Saviour, in the interim be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his Death and Resurrection, descend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>locally</hi> into Hell, there to suffer the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the damn'd. His own words up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Cross, <hi>It is finish'd;</hi> His promise to the penitent Thief, that he should be with him that day in <hi>Paradice,</hi> and his last <hi>resigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his Spirit into the hands of his Father, do all of them apparently contradict it. But yet, though the <hi>bitter Cup</hi> was wholly drank off upon the Cross, 'tis natural to imagine some little <hi>relish</hi> of it to remain behind for a time. Though all his sufferings and <hi>penal</hi> inflictions were ended before his death, yet, I suppose (and I think very naturally) some little <hi>discomposures</hi> of mind, remaining like the <hi>after-droppings</hi> of a shower, which his Soul could not immediately shake off, upon her release from the Body. In allusion to that of <hi>Virgil,</hi>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49931:13"/>
                        <q>
                           <l>Inter quas Phaenissa recens à vulnere Dido</l>
                           <l>Errabat Sylva in Magna—</l>
                        </q> Where the Poet fancies the Ghost of <hi>Dido</hi> being newly releas'd from the pains of Love, could not presently forget her <hi>shady</hi> walks and <hi>melancholy</hi> retirements. Now these <hi>Remains</hi> of Sorrow and <hi>after-disturbances</hi> of mind which cleav'd to the Soul of the <hi>Holy Jesus,</hi> I suppose here to be allay'd by the <hi>Musick</hi> of Angels in his <hi>passage</hi> to <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49931:13"/>
                  <head>An Hymn upon the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuration.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>HAil <hi>King of Glory,</hi> clad in Robes of Light,</l>
                     <l>Out-shining all we here call bright:</l>
                     <l>Hail Light's divinest <hi>Galaxy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hail <hi>Express Image</hi> of the <hi>Deity.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could now thy <hi>Amorous Spouse</hi> thy Beauties view,</l>
                     <l>How would her wounds all bleed anew:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lovely</hi> thou art all o're and bright,</l>
                     <l>Thou <hi>Israel's Glory,</hi> and thou <hi>Gentile's Light.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>But whence this brightness, whence this sudden day?</l>
                     <l>Who did thee thus with light array?</l>
                     <l>Did thy <hi>Divinity</hi> dispence</l>
                     <l>T' its <hi>Consort</hi> a more <hi>liberal</hi> influence?</l>
                     <l>Or did some Curious Angel's <hi>Chymick</hi> Art</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Spirits</hi> of purest light impart,</l>
                     <l>Drawn from the <hi>Native Spring</hi> of day,</l>
                     <l>And wrought into an <hi>Organized</hi> ray?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Howe're twas done, 'tis Glorious and Divine,</l>
                     <l>Thou dost with <hi>radiant wonders</hi> shine.</l>
                     <l>The Sun with his bright Company,</l>
                     <l>Are all <hi>gross Meteors</hi> if compar'd to thee.</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49931:14"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49931:14"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49931:15"/>
                     <l>Thou art the fountain whence their Light does flow,</l>
                     <l>But to thy <hi>will</hi> thine <hi>own</hi> dost owe.</l>
                     <l>For (as at first) thou didst but say,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let there be light,</hi> and strait sprang forth this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>Let now the <hi>Eastern Princes</hi> come and bring</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Tributary</hi> Offering.</l>
                     <l>There needs no <hi>Star</hi> to guide their flight,</l>
                     <l>They'll find thee now, <hi>great King,</hi> by thine <hi>own</hi> light.</l>
                     <l>And thou, my Soul, adore, love and admire,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>follow</hi> this <hi>bright Guide</hi> of <hi>Fire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Do thou thy <hi>Hymns</hi> and <hi>Praises</hi> bring,</l>
                     <l>Whil'st Angels with <hi>Veil'd Faces,</hi> Anthems sing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Parting.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>DEpart! The Sentence of the <hi>Damn'd</hi> I hear;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Compendious</hi> grief, and <hi>black</hi> despair.</l>
                     <l>I now believe the <hi>Schools</hi> with ease,</l>
                     <l>(Tho once an <hi>happy Infidel</hi>)</l>
                     <l>That should the <hi>sense</hi> no torment seize,</l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>Pain</hi> of <hi>Loss</hi> alone would make a <hi>Hell.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Take all, since me of this you Gods deprive,</l>
                     <l>'Tis hardly now worth while to live.</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49931:15"/>
                     <l>Nought in <hi>exchange</hi> can grateful prove,</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Second</hi> Friendship can be found</l>
                     <l>To match my mourning <hi>Widow'd</hi> Love;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eden</hi> is lost, the rest's but <hi>common</hi> ground.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Why are the <hi>greatest Blessings</hi> sent in vain,</l>
                     <l>Which must be lost with <hi>greater pain?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or why do we fondly admire</l>
                     <l>The greatest good which <hi>life</hi> can boast?</l>
                     <l>When Fate will have the <hi>Bliss expire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Life,</hi> with painful <hi>Agonies</hi> 'tis lost.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>How fading are the Joys we dote upon,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Apparitions seen</hi> and <hi>gone:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But those which soonest take their flight,</l>
                     <l>Are the most <hi>exquisite</hi> and <hi>strong,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Angels</hi> visits, <hi>short</hi> and <hi>bright;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Mortality's too <hi>weak</hi> to bear them <hi>long.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <l>No pleasure certainly is so divine</l>
                     <l>As when two Souls in Love combine:</l>
                     <l>He has the <hi>substance</hi> of all bliss,</l>
                     <l>To whom a Vertuous <hi>Friend</hi> is given,</l>
                     <l>So sweet harmonious Friendship is,</l>
                     <l>Add but <hi>Eternity,</hi> you'll make it <hi>Heaven.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <l>The <hi>Minutes</hi> in your conversation spent</l>
                     <l>Were <hi>Festivals</hi> of true content.</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49931:16"/>
                     <l>Here, here, an <hi>Ark</hi> of pleasing <hi>rest,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Soul had found that <hi>restless Dove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My <hi>present</hi> State methought was <hi>best,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I envy'd none <hi>below,</hi> scarce those <hi>above.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <l>But now the better part of me is gone,</l>
                     <l>My Sun is <hi>set,</hi> my Turtle <hi>flown.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tho here and there of <hi>lesser</hi> bliss</l>
                     <l>Some <hi>twinkling</hi> Stars give <hi>feeble</hi> light,</l>
                     <l>Still there a mournful <hi>darkness</hi> is,</l>
                     <l>They shine but just enough to shew 'tis <hi>night.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <l>Fatal divorce! What have I done amiss,</l>
                     <l>To bear such misery as this?</l>
                     <l>The World yields now no real good,</l>
                     <l>All happiness is now become</l>
                     <l>But <hi>painted</hi> and <hi>deluding</hi> food:</l>
                     <l>As meer a <hi>Fiction</hi> as <hi>Elysium.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <l>Well then, since nothing else can please my taste,</l>
                     <l>I'll <hi>ruminate</hi> on pleasures <hi>past.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So when with glorious Visions blest,</l>
                     <l>The waking <hi>Hermit</hi> finds no theme</l>
                     <l>That's grateful to his thoughtful breast,</l>
                     <l>He sweetly <hi>recollects</hi> his pleasing <hi>Dream.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49931:16"/>
                  <head>To a Lady, who asked him, What Life was?</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'TIs not because I <hi>breathe</hi> and <hi>eat,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis not because a vigorous heat</l>
                     <l>Drives <hi>round</hi> my Blood, and does impart</l>
                     <l>Motion to my Pulfe and Heart:</l>
                     <l>'Tis not such proofs as these can give</l>
                     <l>Any assurance that I <hi>Live.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No, no, to <hi>Live</hi> is to <hi>enjoy;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What marrs our <hi>bliss</hi> does <hi>Life</hi> destroy:</l>
                     <l>The days which pass without <hi>Content,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are not <hi>liv'd</hi> properly, but <hi>spent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who says the Damn'd in Hell do <hi>Live?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That word we to the <hi>Blessed</hi> give:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sum</hi> of all whose happiness</l>
                     <l>We by the name of <hi>Life</hi> express.</l>
                     <l>Well then, if this account be true,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Live</hi> is still to Live with <hi>You.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49931:17"/>
                  <head>The third Chapter of <hi>Job</hi> Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrased.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>CUrs'd, ever curs'd be that unhappy day,</l>
                     <l>When first the Suns unwelcome ray</l>
                     <l>I saw with <hi>trembling</hi> eyes, being newly come</l>
                     <l>From the <hi>dark</hi> Prison of the <hi>womb.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When first to me my vital breath was lent,</l>
                     <l>That breath which now must <hi>all</hi> in <hi>sighs</hi> be spent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Let not the Sun his chearing Beams display</l>
                     <l>Upon that <hi>wretched, wretched</hi> day;</l>
                     <l>But mourn in <hi>Sables,</hi> and all over shroud</l>
                     <l>His glories in a <hi>fullen</hi> cloud.</l>
                     <l>Let light to <hi>upper</hi> Regions be confin'd,</l>
                     <l>And all <hi>below</hi> as black as is my <hi>mind.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Curs'd be the night which first began to lay</l>
                     <l>The <hi>ground-work</hi> of this house of Clay:</l>
                     <l>Let it not have the honour to appear</l>
                     <l>In the <hi>Retinue</hi> of the year.</l>
                     <l>Let all the days shun its society,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hate, curse, abandon</hi> it as much as <hi>I.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49931:17"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>Let <hi>Melancholy</hi> call that Night her <hi>own,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then let her sigh, then let her groan:</l>
                     <l>A general grief throughout all Nature spread,</l>
                     <l>With folded arms, and drooping head.</l>
                     <l>All Harps be still, or tun'd to <hi>such</hi> a strain</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Fiends</hi> might hear, and yet not <hi>ease</hi> their <hi>pain.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <l>Let neither Moon nor Stars, with <hi>borrow'd</hi> light,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Checquer</hi> the blackness of that Night:</l>
                     <l>But let a pure <hi>unquestion'd</hi> darkness rear</l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Sooty</hi> Wings all o're the Air;</l>
                     <l>Such as once on th' <hi>Abyss</hi> of <hi>Chaos</hi> lay,</l>
                     <l>Not to be <hi>pierc'd</hi> by <hi>Stars,</hi> scarce by the <hi>edge</hi> of <hi>Day.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <l>Why was there then, ah, why a passage free</l>
                     <l>At once for <hi>life</hi> and <hi>misery?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Why did I not <hi>uncloister'd</hi> from the Womb</l>
                     <l>Take my <hi>next lodging</hi> in a Tomb?</l>
                     <l>Why with such <hi>cruel</hi> tenderness and care</l>
                     <l>Was I <hi>nurs'd</hi> up to Sorrow and Despair?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <l>For now in sweet repose might I have lain</l>
                     <l>Secure from any grief or pain:</l>
                     <l>Untouch'd with care, my Bed I should have made</l>
                     <l>In Death's cool and refreshing <hi>shade.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I should have slept now in a happy place,</l>
                     <l>All calm and silent as the <hi>Empty space.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49931:18"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <l>There where great <hi>Emperours</hi> their heads lay down,</l>
                     <l>Tir'd with the <hi>burthen</hi> of a Crown.</l>
                     <l>There where the Mighty, Popular and Great,</l>
                     <l>Are happy in a <hi>dear</hi> retreat;</l>
                     <l>Enjoy that <hi>solid</hi> Peace which here in vain</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Grotts</hi> and <hi>shady walks</hi> they sought t'obtain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <l>None of Hells Agents can or dare molest</l>
                     <l>This <hi>awful Sanctuary</hi> of rest.</l>
                     <l>No Prisoners sighs, no groanings of the Slave,</l>
                     <l>Disturb the <hi>quiet</hi> of the <hi>Grave.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From toil and labour here they ever cease,</l>
                     <l>And keep a <hi>Sabbath</hi> of sweet <hi>rest</hi> and <hi>peace.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <l>Why then does <hi>Heaven</hi> on Mortals Life bestow</l>
                     <l>When 'tis thus <hi>overtax'd</hi> with woe?</l>
                     <l>Why am I forc'd to live against my will,</l>
                     <l>When all the <hi>good</hi> is <hi>lost</hi> in <hi>ill?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My sighs flow thick, my groans sound from afar,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>falling waters</hi> to the <hi>traveller.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49931:18"/>
                  <head>Seraphic Love.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>'TIs true, <hi>Frail Beauty,</hi> I did once resign</l>
                     <l>To thy <hi>imperious</hi> Charms this Heart of mine:</l>
                     <l>There didst thou <hi>undisturb'd</hi> thy Scepter sway,</l>
                     <l>And I methought was <hi>pleas'd</hi> t' obey.</l>
                     <l>Thou seem'st so lovely, so divine,</l>
                     <l>With such sweet Graces didst thou shine,</l>
                     <l>Thou entertain'st my <hi>Amorous</hi> sense</l>
                     <l>With such <hi>Harmonious</hi> excellence,</l>
                     <l>That, Credulous and Silly I,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>vain,</hi> with <hi>impious</hi> Idolatry,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ador'd</hi> that <hi>Star</hi> which was to lead me to the <hi>Deity.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>But now, thou soft <hi>Enchantress</hi> of the mind,</l>
                     <l>Farewel, a change, a mighty change I find;</l>
                     <l>The Empire of my Heart thou must resign,</l>
                     <l>For I can be no longer <hi>thine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A Nobler, a Diviner Guest,</l>
                     <l>Has took possession of my Breast,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He has,</hi> and must <hi>engross</hi> it all,</l>
                     <l>And yet the room is still too <hi>small.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In vain you tempt my Heart to rove,</l>
                     <l>A fairer object now my Soul does move,</l>
                     <l>It must be all <hi>Devotion,</hi> what before was <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49931:19"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Through <hi>Contemplation's Optics</hi> I have seen</l>
                     <l>Him who is <hi>Fairer than the Sons of men:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Source</hi> of good, the light <hi>Archetypall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Beauty in the <hi>Original.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The fairest of ten thousand, He,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Proportion all and Harmony.</l>
                     <l>All <hi>Mortal Beauty</hi>'s but a ray</l>
                     <l>Of his bright ever-shining day;</l>
                     <l>A little <hi>feeble twinkling</hi> Star,</l>
                     <l>Which now the <hi>Sun</hi>'s in place must <hi>disappear;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>There is but <hi>One</hi> that's <hi>Good,</hi> there is but <hi>One</hi> that's <hi>Fair.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>To thee, thou <hi>only Fair,</hi> my Soul aspires</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Holy Breathings, languishing</hi> desires.</l>
                     <l>To thee m' <hi>inamour'd, panting</hi> Heart does move</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Efforts</hi> of <hi>Ecstatic</hi> Love.</l>
                     <l>How do thy glorious <hi>streams</hi> of Light</l>
                     <l>Refresh my <hi>int ellectual</hi> sight!</l>
                     <l>Tho <hi>broken,</hi> and <hi>strain'd</hi> through a Skreen</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>envious</hi> Flesh that stands between!</l>
                     <l>When shall m' <hi>imprison'd</hi> Soul be free,</l>
                     <l>That she thy <hi>Native uncorrected</hi> Light may see,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>gaze</hi> upon thy <hi>Beatific</hi> Face to all <hi>Eternity?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49931:19"/>
                  <head>Atlas Britannicus denuo instau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nunc age divinum inspira mihi <hi>Phaebe</hi> furorem,</l>
                     <l>Maxima ut <hi>Angliacae</hi> pandatur gloria gentis,</l>
                     <l>Ingenii monumentum ingens, durique laboris,</l>
                     <l>Ut{que} <hi>tuum</hi> celebretur opus: Tu nempe perenni</l>
                     <l>Qui Cursu immensi Stadium Metiris Olympi,</l>
                     <l>Unde omnes <hi>variâ</hi> perlustras lampade terras,</l>
                     <l>Ut <hi>tabulâ</hi> exprimerent quem tu <hi>face</hi> circuis orbem</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Anglis</hi> Author eras. Quis enim sine Numine tantum</l>
                     <l>Moliretur opus, Coeptum aut praestare valeret?</l>
                     <l>Dux operis <hi>Deus</hi> est, <hi>totamque infusa per artus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mens agitat</hi> molem, <hi>divinâ</hi> conditus <hi>arte,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Non nisi <hi>divino</hi> describitur <hi>Auspice</hi> Mundus.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fare age <hi>Calliope</hi> audacis primordia coepti,</l>
                     <l>Quidve <hi>Deum</hi> impulerit tam immensâ involvere curâ</l>
                     <l>Mortales animos, tantos aperire labores.</l>
                     <l>Forte Pater rerum à Summâ <hi>Saturnius</hi> arce</l>
                     <l>Vana hominum studia: &amp; curas speculatus inanes,</l>
                     <l>Quamque levi insurgant Mortalia pectora fastu,</l>
                     <l>Risit, &amp; ad Socios Converso lumine Divos,</l>
                     <l>Terricolisne videtis (ait) quam caeca voluptas</l>
                     <l>Decipere, atque <hi>viam palantis quaerere vitae?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Imperio ut certant Reges, mundique quietem</l>
                     <l>Marte agitant, Modicaque armis tellure potiti</l>
                     <l>Corde tument, capita alta gerunt, titulis{que} superbi</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49931:20"/>
                     <l>Se rerum <hi>Dominos</hi> credunt Mundique Monarchas</l>
                     <l>Adque <hi>orbis</hi> metas <hi>regni</hi> procedere fines!</l>
                     <l>Cernite <hi>quantillo</hi> rudis iste superbiat <hi>Haeres.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Regali incedens passu; quam turget avito</l>
                     <l>Stemmate, &amp; <hi>Augusto</hi> quantum sibi plaudit <hi>agello.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tanquam <hi>aliquid Magnum</hi> in <hi>Nostro</hi> possederit orbe,</l>
                     <l>Nescius in quantum pateant terrestria Molem,</l>
                     <l>Ignarus <hi>quantilla</hi> mei pars cognita Mundi.</l>
                     <l>Quinetiam <hi>Merito</hi> O superi, fraudamur honore,</l>
                     <l>Et Laudum pars magna perit, dum Climata tanta</l>
                     <l>Totque latent, tractusque Maris Coeli{que} profundi,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cimmeria</hi> tanquam Nebula &amp; Caligine Mersi.</l>
                     <l>Quare agite immensi pandatur <hi>Scena</hi> Theatri,</l>
                     <l>Nec Mea terricolas lateant Miracula gentes.</l>
                     <l>Unde Sciant homines quam sit sibi <hi>Curta supellex,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Et Nostrum cumulent <hi>geminato</hi> Numen honore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Est locus <hi>Angliacis</hi> Fama celeberrimus oris,</l>
                     <l>Musarum sedes, decus orbis, cura deorum,</l>
                     <l>Quem te <hi>Phaebe</hi> ferunt terris magis omnibus unum</l>
                     <l>Post-habito Coluisse <hi>Chamo</hi>—</l>
                     <l>Omnigenae hic florent artes, hic Sidere dextro</l>
                     <l>Scire datur rerum Causas, Mundique recessus,</l>
                     <l>Aereas tentare domus, animoque per omnem</l>
                     <l>Ire globum, arcanasque omnes inquirere sedes.</l>
                     <l>Quid si aliquos praestanti animo de <hi>Gente togata</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Queis solito melius finxerunt pectus <hi>Athenae</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Mundi hujus varios jubeam describere tractus,</l>
                     <l>Et tabula <hi>Simulante</hi> Meos aperire Labores.</l>
                     <l>Nulla sit ut Nostro pars terrae Incognita Mundo!</l>
                     <l>Assensere Dii, &amp; plausu reboavit <hi>Olympus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49931:20"/>
                     <l>Protinus aetherea lapsus <hi>Cyllenius</hi> arce</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bellositum</hi> nocte ingreditur, somnoque Sepultis</l>
                     <l>Inspirat <hi>Patriam</hi> per <hi>amica</hi> insomnia Mentem</l>
                     <l>Tollite Cuncta (inquit) coeptosque auferte labores,</l>
                     <l>Grandius instat opus, cunctos terraeque Marisque</l>
                     <l>Indigitare Sinus, Complectique omnia Chartis</l>
                     <l>Quemque implevistis <hi>Fama</hi> nunc <hi>pingere</hi> Mundam.</l>
                     <l>Praecipitate Moras, nec plura effatus; at Illi</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ocyus incubuere omnes,</hi> pariterque laborem</l>
                     <l>Sortiti, artifici designant omnia dextra.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fervet opus;</hi> Coelum, &amp; terras, Campos{que} liquentes,</l>
                     <l>Urbes, Montesque insignes, Fluviosque pererrant,</l>
                     <l>Nullus iter prohibet <hi>Rubicon,</hi> spatia omnia lustrant</l>
                     <l>Quot Sol signa tenens duodena volubilis anni.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ergo <hi>iter incoeptum</hi> peragant, <hi>Carolique Deique</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Auspiciis procedat opus, nec Meta labori</l>
                     <l>Ante esto, quam <hi>defuerit quaerentibus</hi> orbis.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At quae <hi>Magna</hi> tuas Celebrare <hi>Britannia</hi> laudes</l>
                     <l>Musa valet, quot tu palmis, quot digna tropheis,</l>
                     <l>Quot <hi>totum</hi> tuleris <hi>Victricia</hi> Signa per <hi>orbem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Audacique omnes <hi>dextra</hi> deviceris oras!</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roma</hi> triumphales circum <hi>Capitolia</hi> Currus</l>
                     <l>Ducat, &amp; ampla suo indicat solennia <hi>Marti</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Quum Cruor, &amp; Mors, &amp; longi <hi>dispendia</hi> belli</l>
                     <l>Victrices tribuere <hi>Aquilas;</hi> Insignior <hi>Anglis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Accumulatur honos, Solam{que} <hi>haec</hi> pulcra <hi>Britannam</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Palma Manet <hi>Gentem, Calamo</hi> quod <hi>Vicerit orbem.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49931:21"/>
                  <head>Ducis Eboracensis ad Oxonium Processio.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>DUm <hi>tristes</hi> Sacra residerent sede <hi>Camoenae,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Et gemerent <hi>querulo</hi> Secli infortunia plectro,</l>
                     <l>Dum <hi>Socios</hi> miscet gemitus, &amp; Murmure leni</l>
                     <l>It <hi>plorans Helicon,</hi> luctusque <hi>reciprocat</hi> unda,</l>
                     <l>Fama per <hi>Aonias</hi> volitat circumsona ripas,</l>
                     <l>Ut placida aethereos mutarent sede tumultus</l>
                     <l>Ad juga <hi>Maeonidum</hi> Coeli Statione relicta</l>
                     <l>Adventare <hi>Deos. Adeo omnis Magna Serenae</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pompa gravis paci est, placidaeque inimica quieti.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Janique <hi>nova arrectas</hi> pertentant gaudia mentes</l>
                     <l>(Semper enim gessisse ferunt <hi>Pia Corde Camaenas</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Laetitiaque <hi>micant</hi> frontes, jam flore superbit</l>
                     <l>Terra novo, jubar emittit <hi>Sincerius</hi> aether,</l>
                     <l>Inque magis <hi>Festiva</hi> aptantur Carmina Nervi,</l>
                     <l>Vicinosque <hi>Helicon</hi> jam pulsat <hi>Fortius</hi> agros.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ruricolas etiam <hi>Nymphas,</hi> pecorisque Magistros</l>
                     <l>Jam gregis oblitos patriis accersit ab arvis</l>
                     <l>Ad juga <hi>Maeonidum</hi> nova fama, deosque videndi</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ambitiosus</hi> amor. Quae tum, quae lumina vulgi!</l>
                     <l>Qui plausus! plenis quae stabant agmina vicis!</l>
                     <l>Terra angusta viris, <hi>Musisque</hi> angustior amnis</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Defuit,</hi> &amp; Coelum <hi>votis,</hi> &amp; <hi>plausibus</hi> aer.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49931:21"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tandem ubi <hi>Coelicolae</hi> ad placidum venere recessum,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sydereae gentis</hi> Numerosa astante Caterva,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Summissoque</hi> humiles intrarunt <hi>Vertice</hi> portas</l>
                     <l>Obvia Musarum processit turba, Deosque</l>
                     <l>Sic affata una est. Reliquae siluere Sorores</l>
                     <l>Atque <hi>audituras</hi> Volvit <hi>Fons Mollius</hi> undas.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O quae Sidereas liquistis <hi>Numina</hi> sedes,</l>
                     <l>Hospitiumque <hi>humile</hi> in Nostra Conquiritis aula,</l>
                     <l>Jam <hi>Nostri</hi> Salvete <hi>Lares,</hi> Salvete <hi>Penates.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nos <hi>Pia</hi> turba sumus, Superumque addictior aris,</l>
                     <l>Quumque Minaretur Coelo <hi>Titania</hi> pubes</l>
                     <l>Atque affectarent regnum Coeleste <hi>Rebelles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nos nunquam Meritis Cumulare Altaria donis</l>
                     <l>Destitimus, justosque diis persolvere honores.</l>
                     <l>Nec coluisse <hi>piget;</hi> Nos Vestro Numine tutae</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alta</hi> in pace sumus, trahimusque per otia vitana.</l>
                     <l>Quinetiam hoc <hi>uno</hi> plus quam pensamur honore</l>
                     <l>Caetera si defint, quod magna laude feremur</l>
                     <l>Hospitio excepisse <hi>Deos.</hi> Sic fata, recessit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Inde datum sectantur iter, Studioque Videndi</l>
                     <l>Et Sacros adeunt latices, &amp; amoena vireta,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pieridumque</hi> domus lauru Cingente <hi>Verendas,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Foelicesque vocant pariter studioque locoque</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Maeonidas</hi>—</l>
                     <l>Quumque Sat <hi>Aonios</hi> lustrassent Numina Colles,</l>
                     <l>Vivite Foelices (aiunt) hac sede Camoenae.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Vivite concordes, &amp; quam vix <hi>Purpura</hi> Novit</l>
                     <l>Observate fidem, Sacrique à Vertice Collis</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49931:22"/>
                     <l>Despicite insanas <hi>vestri</hi> sine parte pericli</l>
                     <l>Magnatum lites, &amp; Mundi <hi>hinc</hi> spernite pompam,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Protinus ad superas Cesserunt Numina sedes</l>
                     <l>Pieriisque sui rediit pax alma Recessus.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Retirement.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>WEll, I have thought on't, and I find</l>
                     <l>This <hi>busie World</hi> is Non-sense all,</l>
                     <l>I here despair to please my mind,</l>
                     <l>Her sweetest <hi>Honey</hi> is so mix'd with <hi>Gall.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Come then, I'll try how 'tis to be <hi>alone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Live to my self a while, and be my <hi>own.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>I've try'd, and bless the <hi>happy</hi> change;</l>
                     <l>So happy, I could almost vow</l>
                     <l>Never from this <hi>Retreat</hi> to range,</l>
                     <l>For sure I ne'r can be so blest as now.</l>
                     <l>From all th' <hi>allays</hi> of bliss I here am free,</l>
                     <l>I <hi>pitty others,</hi> and none <hi>envy me.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Here in this shady lonely Grove</l>
                     <l>I <hi>sweetly think</hi> my hours away,</l>
                     <l>Neither with <hi>Business</hi> vex'd, nor <hi>Love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which in the <hi>World</hi> bear such <hi>Tyrannic</hi> sway:</l>
                     <l>No Tumults can my <hi>close Apartment find,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Calm as those <hi>Seats above,</hi> which know no Storm nor Wind.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49931:22"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>Let <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>News</hi> embroil the State,</l>
                     <l>Pray what's that to my <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Me?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whatever be the <hi>Kingdom</hi>'s Fate,</l>
                     <l>Here I am sure t' <hi>enjoy</hi> a <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lord of my self, accountable to none,</l>
                     <l>Like the first Man in <hi>Paradice,</hi> alone.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <l>While the <hi>Ambitious vainly</hi> sue,</l>
                     <l>And of the <hi>partial</hi> Stars complain,</l>
                     <l>I stand upon the <hi>Shore</hi> and view</l>
                     <l>The mighty <hi>Labours</hi> of the distant <hi>Main.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'm flush'd with <hi>silent</hi> joy, and smile to see</l>
                     <l>The Shafts of Fortune still drop <hi>short</hi> of <hi>me.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <l>Th' <hi>uneasie Pageantry</hi> of State,</l>
                     <l>And all the <hi>plagues</hi> to <hi>Thought</hi> and <hi>Sense</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are far remov'd; I'm plac'd by Fate</l>
                     <l>Out of the <hi>Read</hi> of all <hi>Impertinence.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thus, tho my <hi>fleeting</hi> Life runs <hi>swiftly</hi> on,</l>
                     <l>'Twill not be <hi>short,</hi> because 'tis <hi>all</hi> my <hi>own.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49931:23"/>
                  <head>The Infidel.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>FArewel <hi>Fruition,</hi> thou grand <hi>Cruel</hi> Cheat,</l>
                     <l>Which first our hopes dost <hi>raise</hi> and then <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Farewel thou <hi>Midwife</hi> to <hi>Abortive</hi> Bliss,</l>
                     <l>Thou <hi>Mystery</hi> of fallacies.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Distance</hi> presents the Object fair,</l>
                     <l>With Charming features and a graceful air,</l>
                     <l>But when we come to <hi>seize</hi> th' inviting prey,</l>
                     <l>Like a <hi>Shy Ghost,</hi> it vanishes away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>So to th' <hi>unthinking</hi> Boy the distant Sky</l>
                     <l>Seems on some Mountain's Surface to relie;</l>
                     <l>He with <hi>ambitious</hi> haste climbs the ascent,</l>
                     <l>Curious to touch the <hi>Firmament:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But when with an unweari'd pace</l>
                     <l>Arriv'd he is at the <hi>long-wish'd-for</hi> place,</l>
                     <l>With Sighs the sad defeat he does deplore,</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Heaven</hi> is <hi>still</hi> as <hi>distant</hi> as <hi>before.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>And yet 'twas longe're I could <hi>throughly</hi> see</l>
                     <l>This grand Impostor's <hi>frequent</hi> Treachery.</l>
                     <l>Tho often Fool'd, yet I should still dream on</l>
                     <l>Of Pleasure in <hi>Reversion.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49931:23"/>
                     <l>Tho still he did my hopes <hi>deceive,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His fair Pretensions I would still <hi>believe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such was my <hi>Charity,</hi> that tho I know</l>
                     <l>And found him <hi>false,</hi> yet I would think him <hi>true.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>But now he shall no more with <hi>shews</hi> deceive,</l>
                     <l>I will no more <hi>enjoy,</hi> no more <hi>believe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>unwary Jugler</hi> has so often shewn</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Fallacies,</hi> that now they'r known.</l>
                     <l>Shall I <hi>trust</hi> on? the Cheat is plain,</l>
                     <l>I <hi>will</hi> not be <hi>impos'd</hi> upon <hi>again.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>'ll view the <hi>Bright appearance</hi> from <hi>afar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But never try to <hi>catch</hi> the falling Star.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>On a Musician, supposed to be mad with Musick.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>POOR dull</hi> mistake of <hi>low</hi> Mortality,</l>
                     <l>To call that <hi>Madness,</hi> which is <hi>Ecstasy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis no disorder of the Brain,</l>
                     <l>His Soul is only <hi>set</hi> t'an <hi>higher strain.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Out-soar he does the Sphere of <hi>Common</hi> sense,</l>
                     <l>Rais'd to Diviner Excellence;</l>
                     <l>But when at highest pitch, his Soul out-flies</l>
                     <l>Not <hi>Reason</hi>'s <hi>Bounds,</hi> but those of <hi>vulgar</hi> Eyes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49931:24"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>So when the <hi>Mystic Sibyl</hi>'s Sacred Breast</l>
                     <l>Was with <hi>Divine Infusions</hi> possest,</l>
                     <l>'Twas <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Madness</hi> thought to be,</l>
                     <l>Which was all <hi>Oracle</hi> and <hi>Mystery.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And so the Soul that's shortly to <hi>Commence</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A Spirit <hi>free</hi> from dregs of Sense,</l>
                     <l>Is thought to <hi>rave,</hi> when She discourses high,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>breathes</hi> the <hi>lofty strains</hi> of <hi>Immortality.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Music, thou <hi>Generous Ferment</hi> of the Soul,</l>
                     <l>Thou universal <hi>Cement</hi> of the <hi>whole,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou <hi>Spring</hi> of Passion, that dost inspire</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Religious Ardours,</hi> and <hi>Poetic Fire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who'd think that <hi>Madness</hi> should b'ascrib'd to thee</l>
                     <l>That <hi>mighty Discord</hi> to thy <hi>Harmony?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But 'twas <hi>such ignorance</hi> that call'd the Gift Divine</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>various Tongues, Rage,</hi> and th' <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>Wine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>But thou, <hi>Seraphic</hi> Soul, do thou advance</l>
                     <l>In thy sweet <hi>Ecstasy,</hi> thy <hi>pleasing</hi> Trance:</l>
                     <l>Let thy brisk passions mount still higher,</l>
                     <l>Till they joyn to the <hi>Element</hi> of <hi>Fire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Soar higher yet, till thou shalt <hi>calmly</hi> hear</l>
                     <l>The Music of a well-tun'd Sphere:</l>
                     <l>Then on the <hi>lumpish mass</hi> look down, and tho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> shalt kno<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Madness</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> for groveling still below </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49931:24"/>
                  <head>The Consolation.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>I Grant 'tis bad, but there is some relief</l>
                     <l>In the <hi>Society</hi> of Grief.</l>
                     <l>'Tis sweet to him that <hi>mourns</hi> to see</l>
                     <l>A <hi>whole</hi> House clad in Sorrow's <hi>Livery.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Grief in <hi>Communion</hi> does <hi>remiss</hi> appear,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>harsher</hi> sounds in <hi>Consort,</hi> which <hi>less</hi> grate the Ear.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Men would not Curse the Stars, did they dispence</l>
                     <l>In <hi>common</hi> their ill Influence.</l>
                     <l>Let none be <hi>rich,</hi> and Poverty</l>
                     <l>Would not be thought so great a Misery.</l>
                     <l>Our discontent is from <hi>comparison;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Were better states <hi>unseen,</hi> each man would like his <hi>own.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Should <hi>partial</hi> Seas <hi>wreck</hi> my poor Ship <hi>alone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I might with cause my Fate bemoan.</l>
                     <l>But since before I <hi>sink,</hi> I see</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Numerous Fleet</hi> of Ships descend with me.</l>
                     <l>Why don't I with <hi>content</hi> my breath resign?</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> will, and in the <hi>greater</hi> ruine <hi>bury</hi> mine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49931:25"/>
                  <head>The Choice.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Stet quicunque volet potens</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aulae culmine lubrico, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>NO, I shan't envy him whoe're he be</l>
                     <l>That stands upon the <hi>Battlements</hi> of State,</l>
                     <l>Stand there who will for me,</l>
                     <l>I'd rather be <hi>secure</hi> than <hi>great.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of being so <hi>high</hi> the <hi>pleasure</hi> is but <hi>small,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But <hi>long the Ruine</hi> if I chance to <hi>fall.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Let me in some sweet shade <hi>serenely lye,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Happy in <hi>leisure</hi> and <hi>obscurity;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whilst others place their joys</l>
                     <l>In <hi>popularity</hi> and <hi>noise.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let my soft minutes <hi>glide obscurely</hi> on</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>subterraneous</hi> streams, <hi>unheard, unknown.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Thus when my days are all in <hi>silence</hi> past,</l>
                     <l>A good <hi>plain Country-man</hi> I'll dye at last.</l>
                     <l>Death cannot chuse but be</l>
                     <l>To him a <hi>mighty</hi> misery,</l>
                     <l>Who to the World was <hi>popularly</hi> known,</l>
                     <l>And dies a <hi>Stranger</hi> to <hi>himself alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49931:25"/>
                  <head>The Meditation.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>IT must be done (my Soul) but 'tis a strange,</l>
                     <l>A dismal and <hi>Mysterious</hi> Change,</l>
                     <l>When thou shalt leave this <hi>Tenement</hi> of Clay,</l>
                     <l>And to an <hi>unknown somewhere</hi> Wing away;</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Time</hi> shall be <hi>Eternity,</hi> and thou</l>
                     <l>Shalt <hi>be</hi> thou know'st not <hi>what,</hi> &amp; <hi>live</hi> thou know'st not <hi>how.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amazing</hi> State! no wonder that we dread</l>
                     <l>To <hi>think</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> or <hi>view</hi> the <hi>Dead.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou'rt all wrapt up in Clouds, as if to thee</l>
                     <l>Our very <hi>Knowledge</hi> had <hi>Antipathy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Death could not a more <hi>Sad</hi> Retinue find,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sickness</hi> and <hi>Pain before,</hi> and <hi>Darkness</hi> all <hi>behind.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Some Courteous Ghost, tell this <hi>great Secrecy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What 'tis you <hi>are,</hi> and we <hi>must</hi> be.</l>
                     <l>You warn us of <hi>approaching</hi> Death, and why</l>
                     <l>May we not know from you what 'tis to <hi>Dye?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But you, having <hi>shot</hi> the Gulph, delight to see</l>
                     <l>Succeeding Souls <hi>plunge</hi> in with <hi>like uncertainty.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49931:26"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>When Life's close Knot by <hi>Writ</hi> from Destiny,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Disease</hi> shall cut, or <hi>Age-unty;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When after some <hi>Delays,</hi> some <hi>dying</hi> Strife,</l>
                     <l>The Soul stands <hi>shivering</hi> on the <hi>Ridge</hi> of Life;</l>
                     <l>With what a <hi>dreadful Curiosity</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Does she <hi>launch</hi> out into the Sea of vast <hi>Eternity.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <l>So when the Spatious Globe was delug'd o're,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>lower holds</hi> could save no more,</l>
                     <l>On th' <hi>utmost</hi> Bough th' astonish'd Sinners stood,</l>
                     <l>And view'd th' <hi>advances</hi> of th' <hi>encroaching</hi> Flood.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O're-topp'd</hi> at length by th' Element's encrease,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>horrour</hi> they resign'd to the <hi>untry'd Abyss.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49931:26"/>
                  <head>The Irreconcilable.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>I Little thought <hi>(my Damon)</hi> once, that <hi>you</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could prove, and what is more, to <hi>me, untrue.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can I <hi>forget</hi> such <hi>Treachery,</hi> and <hi>Live?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mercy</hi> it self would not this Crime forgive.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heaven</hi>'s Gates refuse to let <hi>Apostates</hi> in,</l>
                     <l>No, that's the <hi>Great unpardonable Sin.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Did you not vow by all the Powers above,</l>
                     <l>That you could none but <hi>dear Orinda</hi> love?</l>
                     <l>Did you not swear by all that is Divine,</l>
                     <l>That you would <hi>only</hi> be and <hi>ever</hi> mine?</l>
                     <l>You did, and yet you live <hi>securely</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>And think that <hi>Heaven</hi>'s <hi>false</hi> as well as <hi>you.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Believe me, <hi>Love</hi>'s a thing <hi>much</hi> too <hi>divine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thus to be <hi>Ape'd,</hi> and made a mere <hi>design.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis no less Crime than <hi>Treason here</hi> to <hi>feign,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis Counterfeiting of a <hi>Royal Coin.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But ah! <hi>Hypocrisy</hi>'s no where so common grown,</l>
                     <l>As in <hi>Most Sacred</hi> things, <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49931:27"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>Go seek <hi>new Conquests,</hi> go, you have my leave,</l>
                     <l>You shall not <hi>Grieve</hi> her whom you could <hi>deceive.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I don't <hi>lament,</hi> but <hi>pitty</hi> what you do,</l>
                     <l>Nor take that Love as <hi>lost,</hi> which ne'r was <hi>true.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The way that's left you to <hi>befriend</hi> my Fate,</l>
                     <l>Is now to prove <hi>more constant</hi> in your <hi>Hate.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49931:27"/>
                  <head>A Discourse of the Care and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Time.</head>
                  <p>TO be careful how we manage and employ our Time, is one of the <hi>first</hi> Precepts that is <hi>taught</hi> in the School of Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and one of the <hi>last</hi> that is <hi>learn'd.</hi> The first and <hi>leading</hi> dictate of Prudence is, That a Man propose to himself his true and best interest for his End; and the next is, That he make use of all those means and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities whereby that end is to be attain'd. And betwixt these two there is such a close connexion, that he who does not <hi>do</hi> the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> cannot be supposed to <hi>intend</hi> the <hi>former.</hi> He that is not careful of his actions, shall never perswade me that he seriously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses to himself his best interest, as his <hi>end,</hi> for if he did, he would as seriously apply himself to the regulation of the <hi>other</hi> as the <hi>means.</hi> And so he that is not careful of his Time, cannot in reason be supposed to be careful of his Actions; for if he were, he would certainly have a special regard to the <hi>opportunity</hi> of their performance.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:49931:28"/>
                  <p>But, as I observ'd in the beginning, though this Precept be one of the <hi>Elementary</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Prudence, and stands written in the <hi>first page</hi> of the <hi>Book of Wisdom;</hi> yet such is the sottishness and stupidity of the World, that there is none that is more <hi>slowly learn'd.</hi> And 'tis a prodigious thing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that, although among all the <hi>Talents</hi> which are committed to our <hi>Stewardship,</hi> Time upon several accounts is the most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, yet there is not any one of which the generality of men are more profuse and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardless. Tho it be a thing of that inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable value, that 'tis not distributed to us <hi>intirely,</hi> and at once, like other Blessings, but is <hi>dealt</hi> out in minutes and little parcels, as if man were not fit to be trusted with the <hi>intire</hi> possession of such a <hi>choice</hi> Treasure, yet there are very many that think themselves so <hi>overstock'd</hi> with it, that instead of <hi>husbanding</hi> it to advantage, the main business of their thoughts is how to rid their hands of it, and accordingly they catch at every shadow and opportunity of <hi>relief;</hi> strike in at a venture with the next Companion, and so the <hi>dead Commodity</hi> be <hi>taken off,</hi> care not who be the <hi>Chapman.</hi> Nay, 'tis obvious to observe, that even those persons who are frugal and thrifty
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49931:28"/>in every thing else, are yet extremely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of their best <hi>Revenue,</hi> Time; <hi>Of which alone</hi> (as <hi>Seneca</hi> neatly observes) <hi>'tis a Vertue to be Covetous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither may this Censure be fastned only upon the <hi>unthinking</hi> multitude, the <hi>Sphere</hi> of whose Consideration is supposed to be very <hi>narrow,</hi> and their Apprehension <hi>short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sighted;</hi> but I observe that many of those who set up for Wits, and pretend to a more than ordinary sagacity, and delicacy of Sense, do notwithstanding spend their Time very <hi>unaccountably,</hi> and live away whole days, weeks, and sometimes months together, to as little purpose (tho it may be not so inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently) as if they had been asleep all the while. And this they are so far from being ashamed to own, that they freely boast of it, and pride themselves in it, thinking that it tends to their Reputation, and commends the greatness of their Parts, that they can <hi>support</hi> themselves upon the Natural <hi>stock,</hi> without being beholden to the <hi>Interest</hi> that is brought in by Study and Industry.</p>
                  <p>But if their Parts be so good as they would have others believe, sure they are <hi>worth</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving; if not, they have the more <hi>need</hi> of it. And tho it be an Argument of a <hi>rich</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:49931:29"/>mind, to be able to <hi>maintain</hi> it self without <hi>labour,</hi> and <hi>subsist</hi> without the <hi>advantages</hi> of Study, yet there is no man that has such a portion of Sense, but will understand the use of his Time better than to put it to the tryal. Greatness of Parts is so far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a discharge from <hi>Industry,</hi> that I find Men of the most exquisite Sense in all Ages were always most curious of their Time: Nay, the most Intelligent of all Created Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings (who may be allow'd to pass a truer estimate upon things than the finest Mortal Wit) value Time at a high rate. <hi>Let me go</hi> (says the Angel to the importunate Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch) <hi>for the day breaketh.</hi> And therefore I very much suspect the excellency of those mens Parts, who are dissolute and careless mis-spenders of their Time: For if they were men of <hi>any thoughts,</hi> how is it possible but these should be some in the number? <hi>(viz.)</hi>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That this Life is wholly in order to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that Time is that <hi>sole opportunity</hi> that God has given us for transacting the great business of Eternity: That our work is great, and our day of working short, much of which also is lost and render'd use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, through the cloudiness and darkness of the <hi>Morning,</hi> and the thick vapours and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49931:29"/>unwholesome foggs of the <hi>Evening;</hi> the ignorance and inadvertency of <hi>Youth,</hi> and the Diseases and Infirmities of <hi>Old Age:</hi> That our portion of Time is not only short, as to its duration, but also uncertain in the possession: That the loss of it is irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the loser, and profitable to no body else: That it shall be severely accounted for at the great Judgement, and lamented in a sad Eternity.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that considers these things (and sure he must needs be a <hi>very unthinking</hi> man that does not) will certainly be choice of his Time, and look upon it no longer as a bare state of <hi>duration,</hi> but as an <hi>Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> and consequently will let no part of it (no <hi>considerable</hi> part at least) slip away either <hi>unobserv'd</hi> or <hi>unimprov'd.</hi> This is the most effectual way that I know of to secure to ones self the <hi>Character</hi> of a Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>here,</hi> and the <hi>reward</hi> of one <hi>hereafter.</hi> Whereas the <hi>vain Enthusiastic</hi> Pretenders to the <hi>Gift</hi> of Wit, that trifle away their Time, betray the <hi>shallowness</hi> and <hi>poverty</hi> of their Sense to the <hi>discerning few;</hi> or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may pass for here among their fellow Mortals, do most infallibly make themselves <hi>cheap</hi> in the sight of <hi>Angels.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49931:30"/>
                  <head>Of Solitude.</head>
                  <p>IT has been urg'd as an Objection, by some <hi>Atheistical</hi> Persons, against the existence of a God, that if there had been such a perfect Being, who was <hi>compleatly</hi> happy in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of himself, he would never have gone about to make a World. Now, tho this Objection contributes nothing to the support of Atheism (the design of God in Creating the World being not to <hi>increase</hi> his happiness, but to <hi>Communicate</hi> it) yet it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds upon this true supposition, That <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> is a <hi>Blessing.</hi> It is so, and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>respectively,</hi> and in reference to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent circumstances of the World, and the Necessities of this Life, but also <hi>simply,</hi> and in its own Nature; since it shall be an <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessory</hi> to our bliss in Heaven, and add many <hi>moments</hi> to the <hi>weight</hi> of <hi>Glory.</hi> Neither will the truth of this assertion be at all wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd by alledging that no benefit or advantage accrues to God by it, for that it becomes unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to him (tho a Blessing in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) is purely by accident, because God emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently containing in himself all <hi>possible</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49931:30"/>good, is uncapable of any <hi>New</hi> Accession.</p>
                  <p>And as Society is in its own nature an instrument of Happiness, so is it made much more so by the indigencies and infirmities of Men. Man, of all Creatures in the World, is least qualify'd to live alone, because there is no Creature that has so many necessities to be reliev'd. And this I take to be one of the great <hi>Arts</hi> of Providence, to secure mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual amity and the <hi>reciprocation</hi> of good turns in the World, it being the Nature of Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, like common danger, to indear men to one another, and make them herd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like <hi>Fellow-Sailors</hi> in a <hi>Storm.</hi> And this indeed is the true case of Mankind, we all Sail in one <hi>battom,</hi> and in a <hi>rough</hi> Sea, and stand in need of one anothers help at every turn, both for the <hi>Necessities</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshments</hi> of Life. And therefore I am very far from commending the undertaking of those <hi>Asceties,</hi> that out of a pretence of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves <hi>unspotted from the World,</hi> take up their quarters in <hi>Desarts,</hi> and utterly abandon all Humane Society. This is in short (to say no more of it) to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into an incapacity either of <hi>doing</hi> any good to the World, or of receiving any from it: and certainly that can be no desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49931:31"/>state. No, this <hi>Eremetical</hi> way of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is utterly inconsistent with the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances and Inclinations of Humane Nature; he must be a God, <hi>Self-sufficient</hi> and <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi> that is fit for this state of absolute and perfect Solitude, and in this <hi>rigorous</hi> sense, <hi>It is not good for man</hi> (tho in <hi>Paradice</hi> it self) <hi>to be alone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But tho Society, as 'tis opposed to a state of perfect and perpetual Solitude, be a Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, yet considering how little of it there is in the World that is <hi>good,</hi> I think it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visable for every man that has sense and thoughts enough, to be his own Companion, (for certainly there is more required to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie a man for his <hi>own</hi> company than for <hi>other</hi> men's) to be as frequent in his Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as he can, and to communicate as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle with the World as is consistent with the duty of doing good, and the discharge of the common offices of Humanity. 'Tis true indeed (as <hi>Seneca</hi> says) <hi>Miscendae &amp; alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandae sunt Solitudo &amp; frequentia: Solitude and Company are to have their turns, and to be interplaced.</hi> But Wise-men use to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the largest share of their Lives to the the former, and let the <hi>best</hi> and <hi>most</hi> of their Time go to make up the <hi>Canonical Hours</hi> of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49931:31"/>Study, Meditation and Devotion. And for this, besides the practice of Wise-men, we have the <hi>Authentic</hi> example of our B. Lord himself, Who, (as 'tis reasonably supposed (for he had pass'd the thirtieth year of his Life before he enter'd upon the stage of Action, and then also sought all opportunities to be alone, and oftentimes purchas'd Retirement at the expence of Night-watches) allotted the greatest part of his little Time here on Earth to Privacy and Retirement; and 'tis highly probable, would have liv'd much more reservedly, had not the peculiar busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of his function made it necessary for him to be conversant in the World. The incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our Lord lay more toward the <hi>Contemplative</hi> way of Life, tho the interest of Mankind engaged him oftentimes upon the <hi>Active.</hi> And 'tis very observable, that there is scarce any one thing which he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed to grace with so many marks and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of favour and respect as he did So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude. Which are thus summ'd up by the excellent Pen of a very great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of Learning and Language;
<note place="margin">The Great Exemplar.</note>
                     <hi>It was Solitude and Retirement in which Jesus kept his Vigils; the desart places heard him pray, in a privacy he was born, in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49931:32"/>the Wilderness he fed his thousands, upon a Mountain apart he was transfigured, upon a Mountain he died, and from a Mountain he ascended to his Father. In which Retirements his Devotion certainly did receive the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of convenient circumstances, and himself in such dispositions twice had the opportunities of Glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Indeed, the <hi>Satisfactions</hi> and <hi>Advantages</hi> of Solitude (to a person that knows how to improve it) are very great, and far tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scending those of a <hi>Secular</hi> and <hi>Popular</hi> Life. First, as to Pleasure and Satisfaction, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever considers the great variety of mens hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, the peevishness of some, the pride and conceitedness of others, and the imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of most; he that considers what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable <hi>terms of Communion</hi> some persons impose upon those that partake of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; how rare 'tis for a man to light upon a Company, where, as his first Salutation, he shall not presently have a Bottle thrust to his Nose; he, I say, that considers these and a thousand more grievances, wherewith the <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>ill nature</hi> of men have conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>burthen</hi> Society, will find, take one time with another, Company is an occasion of almost as much <hi>displeasure</hi> as <hi>pleasure.</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49931:32"/>Whereas in the mean time the Solitary and Contemplative man sits as safe in his Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as one of <hi>Homer's Heroes</hi> in a Cloud, and has this only trouble from the follies and extravagancies of men, that he <hi>pitties</hi>them. He does not, it may be, laugh so loud, but he is better <hi>pleas'd:</hi> He is not perhaps so often <hi>merry,</hi> but neither is he so often <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gusted;</hi> he lives to himself and God, full of Serenity and Content.</p>
                  <p>And as the <hi>Pleasures</hi> and <hi>Satisfactions</hi> of Solitude exceed those of a Popular Life, so also do the <hi>Advantages.</hi> Of these there are two sorts, <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Intellectual;</hi> to both which Solitude is a <hi>particular</hi> friend. As to the first, it is plain that Solitude is the proper opportunity of Contemplation, which is both the <hi>Foundation</hi> and the <hi>Perfection</hi> of a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Life. <hi>It is</hi> (as the same excellent Person fore-cited says elsewhere of a single Life) <hi>the huge advantage of Religion, the great opportunity for the Retirements of Devotion, which being empty of Cares is full of Prayers, being unmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with the World is apt to converse with God, and by not feeling the warmth of a too forward and indulgent Nature, flames out with holy Fires, till it be burning like the Cherubim and the most extasy'd Order of holy and unpolluted Spirits.</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49931:33"/>And for this reason 'twas that the Ancients chose to build their Altars and Temples in Groves and Solitary Recesses, thereby inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating, that Solitude was the best opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Religion.</p>
                  <p>Neither are our <hi>intellectual</hi> advantages less indebted to Solitude. And here, tho I have in a great measure anticipated this consideration (there being nothing neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily required to compleat the Character of a Wise-man, besides the knowledge of God and himself) yet I shall not confine my self to this instance, but deduce the matter further, and venture to affirm that all kinds of <hi>Speculative</hi> knowledge as well as <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> are best improved by Solitude. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is much talk about the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of keeping Great men company, and thereupon 'tis usually reckon'd among the <hi>disadvantages</hi> of a <hi>Country</hi> life, that those of that condition want the opportunities of a <hi>Learned Conversation.</hi> But to confess the truth, I think there is not so much in it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> people generally imagine. Indeed, were the Souls of men lodg'd in <hi>transparent cases,</hi> that we might read their thoughts; would they <hi>communicate</hi> what they know, were it the fashion to discourse learnedly, 'twer<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49931:33"/>worth while to frequent the <hi>Cabals</hi> of Great men: But when it shall be counted a piece of <hi>errant Pedantry,</hi> and defect of good breeding to start any Question of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Company; when every man is as shy of his Notions as of a <hi>Fairy-treasure;</hi> and makes his Head not a Repository or <hi>Exchequer</hi> of Knowledge, but a <hi>Grave</hi> to bury it in: A man may be a constant at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant at the <hi>Conclaves</hi> of Learned men all his life long, and yet be no more the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser for't than a <hi>Book-worm</hi> is for dwelling in <hi>Libraries.</hi> And therefore, to speak inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuously, I don't see for my part wherein the great advantage of great Conversation lies, as the humours of men are pleas'd to order it. Were I to inform my self in busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and the management of affairs, I would sooner talk with a plain illiterate Farmer or Trades-man than the greatest <hi>Vertuoso</hi> of <hi>The Society;</hi> and as for Learning (which is the only thing they are supposed able to discourse well of) <hi>that</hi> in point of <hi>Civility</hi> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline: So that I find I must take refuge at my Study at last, and there <hi>redeem</hi> the Time that I have <hi>lost</hi> among the <hi>Learned.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:49931:34"/>
                  <head>A Discourse concerning Heroic Piety.</head>
                  <p>SInce the Practice of Religion in general is not only the <hi>Natural Instrument</hi> of our <hi>present</hi> Happiness, but also the <hi>only</hi> and <hi>indispensable condition</hi> of our <hi>Future,</hi> one would think there were but little left for the Orator to do here, the naked efficacy of Self-love, and a serious consideration of our true and main Interest, being sufficient to engage us upon Religious performances. But he that shall undertake to recommend the Practice of <hi>Heroic Piety,</hi> has a much hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier task, not only because he perswades to <hi>higher</hi> degrees of Vertue, but because he is to address himself wholly to a <hi>weaker</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For since our <hi>interest</hi> is secured by the performance of <hi>necessary</hi> Duty, there remains nothing but a Principle of <hi>Generosity</hi> to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry us on to the higher <hi>advances,</hi> the more glorious <hi>Atchievements</hi> in Religion. And what small probability there is that it will often do so, may appear from the ill
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49931:34"/>success of the former and more prevailing Principle. For if the greatest interest ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable can prevail with so very few to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what is indispensably necessary to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it, sure there is little hopes that <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosity,</hi> which is a much <hi>weaker</hi> Principle, should engage <hi>many</hi> upon <hi>greater</hi> perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances.</p>
                  <p>But yet, notwithstanding these discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, since our Blessed Saviour has taught us to pray, not only for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of God's will in <hi>general,</hi> but that it be <hi>done on Earth as it is in Heaven;</hi> that is, with the greatest zeal, readiness and alacrity, with all the degrees of <hi>Seraphic</hi> ardency that frail Mortality is capable of, I think a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasive</hi> to <hi>Heroic Piety</hi> may be a proper and useful undertaking; it being very reasonable we should make that the object of our <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,</hi> which our Saviour thought fit to make the matter of our <hi>Prayers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In discoursing upon this subject, I shall proceed in this Method. 1. I shall state the notion of <hi>Heroic Piety,</hi> and shew what I mean by it. 2. I shall demonstrate that there is such a thing. And 3. I shall offer some <hi>Perswasives</hi> to recommend the practice of it.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:49931:35"/>
                  <p>The Notion of <hi>Heroic</hi> Piety will be best understood by considering what the Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists mean by <hi>Heroic</hi> Vertue. For the one carries the same proportion in <hi>Religion</hi> that the other does in <hi>Morality.</hi> But before I proceed to explain the <hi>Thing,</hi> I suppose it will not be amiss to give some short account of the <hi>Name.</hi> That it is derived from the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, is very obvious, all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty is concerning the derivation of the <hi>Greek</hi> word it self. And here I find the Grammarians are very much divided; some derive it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but that seems some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hard; others derive it from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause 'twas supposed by the Ancients that the Souls of the <hi>Heroes</hi> had their abode in the Air, where they had a near prospect of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affairs; and accordingly <hi>Xenon</hi> in <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertius, lib.</hi> 7. calls <hi>Heroes</hi> the Souls of wise men separated from their Bodies, and ranging about in the Air; others derive it from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Heroes are a kind of <hi>terrestrial</hi> Gods, according to that definition which <hi>Lucian</hi> gives of an <hi>Hero,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, one that is neither God nor man, but a compound of both. Others derive it from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the name of <hi>Juno,</hi> who was the President Goddess of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49931:35"/>the Air, intimating thereby either the Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or the light aereal Nature of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes.</hi> And this Etymology I remember is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of by St. <hi>Austin, lib.</hi> 10. <hi>de Civ. Dei, cap.</hi> 21. But methinks the most natural and significant one is that of <hi>Plato,</hi> who derives it from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, because of that ardent and passionate Love which the <hi>Heroes</hi> are suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to have for God. And as the word <hi>Hero</hi> is very doubtful as to its Etymology, so is it also various in its acceptation. Sometimes it is attributed to illustrious and eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages while <hi>living,</hi> such as act and live above the ordinary strain of Mortality, and render it a very disputable Point whether they are Gods or men. A Character which <hi>Homer</hi> gives of the great <hi>Hector, Iliad</hi> ω.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And in this sense the word <hi>Hero</hi> is used by <hi>Hesiod,</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>—</l>
                     </q> Sometimes by Heroes are meant the Souls of wise and good men departed, as is evident
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49931:36"/>from the fore-cited testimony in <hi>Laertius.</hi> But in the <hi>Platonic</hi> Philosophy by <hi>Heroes</hi> is understood a middle sort of Being, inferiour to those whom they stile the <hi>Immortal Gods,</hi> and superiour to Man; as is to be seen at large in <hi>Hierocles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beyond these three acceptations of the word, I do not know of any other. But this is certain, that in whatsoever sense it is used, it always denotes something great and extraordinary. So that from hence 'tis easie to collect what is meant by <hi>Heroic Vertue, (viz.)</hi> Such a vehement and intense pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a mans last and best end, as engages him upon such excellent and highly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable actions, which advance him much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ordinary level of humane Nature, and which he might wholly omit, and yet still maintain the Character of a good man. <hi>Aristot.</hi> in his <hi>Ethics, l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 1. calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that Vertue that is above us. By which, I suppose, he does not mean that it is above our reach and unattainable, but that it i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> above our obligation, and that when it i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> attain'd, it will elevate us above our selves.</p>
                  <p>In proportion to this Notion of Heroi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Vertue, I understand by <hi>Heroic Piety</hi> thos<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> excellent degrees and eminencies of Religion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49931:36"/>which, tho to arrive at be extremely lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet we may fall short of them without Sin, God having not bound them upon us as parts of <hi>Duty,</hi> or made them the <hi>Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of our Salvation, but only recommended them by way of <hi>Counsel,</hi> and left them as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of <hi>Generosity.</hi> Of this sort are those high and singular Exercises of Religion which are the fruits and effects of a profound and steady contemplation of God: Such as are the passionate applications of <hi>Seraphic</hi> Love, acts of ecstatic joy and complacency in the Perfections of the Divine Nature, holy trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Zeal and Devotion, Praise and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: earnest contentions and very numerous returns of Prayer, actual references of our most natural and indifferent actions to Gods glory, extraordinary works of Charity, great severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Mortification and Self-denial, abstemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness from many lawful Pleasures, perpetual <hi>Celebacy,</hi> and whatsoever else are the excellent products of a <hi>contemplative</hi> and <hi>affectionate</hi> Religion.</p>
                  <p>Thus far of the Notion of <hi>Heroic Piety.</hi> I come now to my second Undertaking, which was to shew that there is such a thing. Tho universality and sincerity of Obedience be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dispensably required of every Christian, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49931:37"/>consequently every part of Religion obliges under the penalty of Damnation as to its <hi>kind,</hi> yet that there may be some <hi>degrees</hi> to the attainment of which we are not so obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, will evidently appear from the proof of this one single Proposition, That every one is not bound to do what is <hi>best.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness of which Proposition appears from the very nature of the thing; for since that which is <hi>Best</hi> is a <hi>Superlative,</hi> it necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily supposes the <hi>Positive</hi> to be <hi>good:</hi> And if so, then we are not bound to that which is <hi>best,</hi> for if we were, then that which is <hi>only good</hi> would be <hi>evil,</hi> (it being short of what we are bound to) which is contrary to the supposition.</p>
                  <p>This Argument I take to be <hi>Demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and therefore 'twould be a kind of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation</hi> in me to alledge any more. But however, for the clearer eviction and strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er confirmation of this Assertion, I farther consider, that the Scripture consists of <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels</hi> as well as <hi>Commands.</hi> This distinction, however denied by some in the heat of their <hi>ingagements</hi> against Popery,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.12. <hi>and</hi> 21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.6.7.25.38. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6.</note> is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimated in several places of the New Testament, and allow'd by the best of our Divines. Now if
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49931:37"/>some things are matter of Counsel onely, 'tis obvious to conclude two things. 1. From their being <hi>counsell'd,</hi> that they are good (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being matter of Counsel but what is so) and secondly, from their being <hi>only</hi> counsell'd, that they do not oblige, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently, that there are some degrees of good that we are not obliged to.</p>
                  <p>It is farther observable, that in Scripture there is mention made of a threefold Will of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>That Will which is good, that which is well-pleasing, and that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> The first of these denotes absolute <hi>Duty,</hi> the two last the various degrees of <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Heroic</hi> Excellence. Thus for St. <hi>Paul</hi> to preach the Gospel to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> was an Act of strict Duty which he could not leave undone without incurring that woe which he annexes to the omission of it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>But to preach without charging them was an instance of Generosity,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact.</note>
                     <hi>and in that respect there was room for boasting.</hi> Thus again, for a <hi>Jew</hi> to allot the tenth part of his Revenue every third year toward the relief of the Poor, was an act of express Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in doing of that, he would but satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49931:38"/>the obligation of the Law; But now if in his charitable contributions he should ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed that proportion, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of the excess, so would the degrees of his Perfection be. Thus again in the matter of <hi>Devotion,</hi> daily Prayer is generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to be a <hi>Duty,</hi> and by some <hi>Criticks</hi> that it be <hi>twice</hi> perform'd, in proportion to the returns of the Jewish Sacrifices, Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening; But now if a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously disposed Christian should add a <hi>third</hi> time, or out of <hi>abundance</hi> of zeal should come up to the <hi>Psalmist</hi>'s resolution of <hi>(Seven times a day will I praise thee)</hi> this would be a <hi>free-will</hi> Offering, <hi>well pleasing</hi> and of <hi>sweet savour,</hi> but not <hi>commanded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From these and many other instances, which, if necessary, I could easily produce, it plainly appears that Religion does not consist in an <hi>indivisable point,</hi> but has a <hi>Latitude,</hi> and is capable of <hi>more</hi> and <hi>less,</hi> and consequently there is room for <hi>voluntary Oblations</hi> and Acts of <hi>Heroic Piety.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I know it is usually objected here, that what is supposed to be thus <hi>Heroically</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, is <hi>inclusively</hi> enjoyn'd by vertue of those comprehensive words, <hi>(Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49931:38"/>thy Soul, &amp;c.)</hi> But, I conceive, that all which is intended by that phrase, will amount to no more than, First, a <hi>sincere</hi> love of God, as 'tis opposed to that which is <hi>partial</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided;</hi> and secondly, such a degree of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him, as admits of nothing into <hi>Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition</hi> with him. And thus far reach the <hi>Boundaries</hi> of indispensable Duty, it being impossible that he who does not love God in this <hi>sense</hi> and <hi>degree,</hi> should keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. But beyond this, there are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degrees, which, because we may fall short of without sin, are the more excellent when attain'd. So that in this Precept of loving God, as in all other instances of Religion, there is a great latitude, it being very possible for two Persons to love God <hi>sincerely</hi> and with their <hi>whole Soul,</hi> and yet in different mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures (which is observ'd even among the Angels, the <hi>Seraphins</hi> having their name from their <hi>excess</hi> of <hi>Love</hi>) nay, for the same Person alwayes to love God <hi>sincerely,</hi> and yet at some times to exceed himself, and with his Saviour (who to be sure never fail'd of <hi>necessary</hi> Duty) to <hi>pray yet more earnestly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is another Objection yet behind, which I think my self concern'd to answer, as well in my <hi>own</hi> defence as that of my <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:49931:39"/>Some perhaps may be so weak to imagine, that by asserting such a thing as <hi>Heroick Piety,</hi> and that a Christian may do <hi>more</hi> than he is commanded, I too much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Doctrine of <hi>Supererogation.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess the word <hi>Supererogation,</hi> however inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent as to its primitive acceptation, does now sound somewhat <hi>odly,</hi> and therefore I am the more willing to decline it; tho I very much question whether the <hi>Papists</hi> are not some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing odiously represented in this point. But my business is not to vindicate them, but my self, in order to which I consider, that <hi>for a Man to do more than he is commanded,</hi> is an ambiguous expression, and may denote either that he can perform the <hi>whole</hi> Law of God and <hi>more,</hi> or that, tho he fail of his Duty in many Instances, and consequently with the rest of Mankind, is <hi>concluded under Sin;</hi> Yet in some others he may exceed it, by <hi>pressing forward</hi> to some degrees of excellency he is not obliged to. I do not assert the <hi>former</hi> of these, but the <hi>latter,</hi> and if the <hi>Doctors</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> mean no more by their Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation than this latter Notion of the word imports (and I must ingenuously confess it does not yet appear to me that they do) I cannot but acknowledge that I am so far a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49931:39"/>
                     <hi>Papist,</hi> for I really believe, and I think I have sufficiently proved, that there are certain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in <hi>Religion,</hi> which we are not obliged to under Pain of Sin, and consequently that he who arrives so far, does (according to the <hi>latter</hi> notion of the <hi>Phrase</hi>) do <hi>more then he is commanded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having in the foregoing <hi>Periods</hi> stated the Notion of <hi>Heroick Piety,</hi> and demonstrated that there is such a thing, I proceed now to my third and last undertaking, which was to offer some Perswasives to recommend the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of it. First then, I consider that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the Perfection of a Man, the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and accomplishment of that part of him wherein he resembles his Maker, the pursuance of his best and last end, and consequently his <hi>Happiness.</hi> And will a man set <hi>bounds</hi> to his <hi>Happiness?</hi> Will he be no more happy than he is <hi>commanded,</hi> no more than what will just serve to secure him from a <hi>miserable</hi> Eternity? Is not Happiness desirable for it <hi>self,</hi> as well as for the avoiding of <hi>Misery?</hi> Why then do we deal with it as with <hi>dangerous Physick,</hi> weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it by Grains and Scruples and nice Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions? Why do we drink so <hi>moderately</hi> of the <hi>River</hi> of <hi>Paradise,</hi> so <hi>sparingly</hi> of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49931:40"/>
                     <hi>Well</hi> of <hi>Life?</hi> Are we affraid of making too nigh advances to the State of Angels, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>too</hi> like God, of <hi>antedating</hi> Heaven? Are we affraid our Happiness will flow in too <hi>thick</hi> upon us, that we shall not bear up against the Tide, but sink under the too <hi>powerful</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment? Hereafter indeed, when we are blest with the <hi>Beatific Vision,</hi> and the Glories of the Divine Brightness shall flash too <hi>strong</hi> upon our Souls, so that our Happiness begins to be <hi>lessen'd</hi> by its <hi>greatness;</hi> We may then with the Angels that attend the Throne, <hi>veil</hi> our Faces, and <hi>divert</hi> some of the too <hi>exuberant</hi> blessedness: But now in this <hi>Region</hi> we are far enough from being <hi>under</hi> the <hi>Line,</hi> there is no danger of such <hi>Extremity,</hi> but rather the contrary, and therefore it would be now most advisable for us to be as <hi>Happy,</hi> and to that end, as <hi>Religious</hi> as we can.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I consider, that since God, out of the abundance of his <hi>overflowing</hi> and <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative</hi> Goodness, was pleas'd to create and design man for the best of Ends, the fruition of himself in endless Happiness, and since he has prescribed no other Conditions for the attainment of this Happiness; but that we would live happily here in this State of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, having made nothing our Duty but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49931:40"/>what would have been best for us to do whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had commanded it or no, and has thereby declared, that he is so far only pleas'd with our Services to <hi>him</hi> as they are benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to <hi>our selves;</hi> this must needs be a most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing engagement to one that has the least spark of Generosity or Ingenuity, to do som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the sake of so <hi>good</hi> a God, beyond the Measures of Necessity, and the regards of his main and final interest. This is the <hi>only Tribute</hi> of Gratitude we are capable of paying God for giving us such good, such reasonable, and righteous Laws. Had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of our eternal welfare been never so hard, arbitrary, and contradictory to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Happiness, yet mere interest would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to perform <hi>necessary Duty,</hi> and shall we do no more out of a principle of <hi>Love</hi> to our excellent Lawgiver, for making our <hi>present Happiness</hi> the <hi>Condition</hi> of our <hi>future?</hi> Shall the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> constrain us to do no more then what we would do <hi>merely</hi> for the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>our selves?</hi> shall we stint our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances to him, who sets no Measures to his Love of us? Can our Generosity be ever more seasonably employ'd than in endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to please him in <hi>extraordinary</hi> Measures, whose <hi>Pleasure</hi> is to see us <hi>happy</hi> even <hi>while</hi>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49931:41"/>we <hi>please</hi> him? For so is the will of the wise and good Governour of the World, that in serving <hi>him</hi> we should serve <hi>our selves,</hi> and like <hi>Adam</hi> in his dressing and cultivation of Paradise, at the same time discharge the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment which God sets us about, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult our <hi>own</hi> Convenience: So that it fares with us in our religious Exercises as with the Votary that sacrifices at the Altar, who all the while he <hi>pleases</hi> and serves his <hi>God, enjoys</hi> the <hi>perfumes</hi> of his <hi>own Incense.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I consider, that every Man has a restless Principle of Love implanted in his Nature, a certain <hi>Magnetism</hi> of Passion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (according to the <hi>Platonic</hi> and true noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Love) he continually aspires to som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more excellent than himself, either really or apparently, with a design and inclination to perfect his Being. This affection and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of Mind <hi>all</hi> Men have, and at <hi>all</hi> times. Our other Passions ebb and flow like the Tide, have their Seasons and Periods like <hi>intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Feavers.</hi> But this of Love is as constant as our <hi>Radical</hi> heat, as inseparable as <hi>thought,</hi> as even and equal as the Motions of Time. For no man does or can desire to be happy more at one time than at another, because he desires it always in the highest degree <hi>possible.</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49931:41"/>'Tis true, his Love, as to particular objects, may increase or decrease, according to the various apprehensions he has of their excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies; but then, like <hi>Motion</hi> in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse, what it loses in one part it gains in another; so that in the whole it remains al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways alike, and the same. Now this <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Principle which every man receives with his Soul, and which is breath'd into him with the breath of Life, must necessarily have an object about which it may exercise it self, there being no such thing in <hi>Love</hi> (if in <hi>Nature</hi>) as an <hi>Element</hi> of <hi>Self-sufficient</hi> Fire. For tho we may easily and truly frame an abstract notion of Love or Desire in <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> yet if we respect its <hi>real</hi> existence, we shall as soon find <hi>First Matter</hi> without <hi>Form,</hi> as <hi>Love</hi> without a particular <hi>Object.</hi> And, as 'tis necessary to the very being of Love that it have an object, so is it to our content and happiness, that it be a proportionate and satisfying one; for otherwise that passion which was intended as an instrument of <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness,</hi> will prove an <hi>affliction</hi> and <hi>torment</hi> to us. Now there is but one such object to be found, and that is God. In the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Passions to other things, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Poet is exceeding necessary,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49931:42"/>
                     <q>Quicquid amas cupias non placuisse nimis. <bibl>
                           <hi>Martial.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </q>
                     <hi>That we should be very cantious how far we suffer our selves to be engaged in the love of any thing,</hi> because there is nothing but <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment</hi> in the <hi>enjoyment,</hi> and <hi>uncertainty</hi> in the <hi>possession.</hi> We must needs therefore be miserable in our Love, unless God be the object of it. But neither is our happiness sufficiently secured by making <hi>God</hi> the object of our Love, unless we <hi>concenter</hi> our whole affections upon him, and (in the strictest sense of the Phrase) <hi>love him with all our Heart and with all our Soul.</hi> For otherwise, whatever portion of our Love does not run in this Channel, must necessarily fix upon disproportionate and unsatisfying objects, and consequently be an instrument of discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to us. 'Tis necessary therefore to the compleating of our happiness, that that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject should <hi>engross</hi> all our affections to it self, which only can satisfie them;
<note place="margin">Marsilius Fici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Tom. 2. pag. 315.</note> and (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the comparison of an ingenious <hi>Platonist</hi>) that our minds should have the same ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitude to God that the Eye has to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49931:42"/>Light. Now the Eye does not only love Light above other things, but <hi>delights</hi> in nothing else. I confess, such an <hi>absolute</hi> and <hi>entire Dedication</hi> of our love to God as this, is not always practicable in this Life. It is the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and happiness of those <hi>confirm'd</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits who are so swallow'd up in the <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions</hi> of <hi>Eternity,</hi> and so perpetually ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish'd with the Glories of the Divine Beauty, that they have not the <hi>power</hi> to turn aside to any <hi>other</hi> object. But tho this Superlative Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Divine Love be not attainable on this side of the <hi>thick darkness,</hi> it being the proper effect of <hi>open Vision,</hi> and not of <hi>Contemplation;</hi> yet however, by the help of this latter, we may arrive to many degrees of it, and the more entire and undivided our love is to God, the fewer-disappointments and dissatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we shall meet with in the World, which is a very strong ingagement to <hi>Heroic Piety.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, I consider, that the degrees of our <hi>Reward</hi> shall be proportionable to the degrees of our <hi>Piety:</hi> We shall reap as plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully as we sow, and at the great day of Retribution, we shall find, that besides the general <hi>Collation</hi> of Happiness, peculiar Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronets
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49931:43"/>of Glory are prepared for <hi>Eminent</hi> Saints. Indeed, all hearty and sincere lovers of God and Religion shall partake of the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> but some shall sit near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the Throne than others, and enjoy a more <hi>intimate</hi> perception of the <hi>Divine Beauty.</hi> All the true <hi>Followers</hi> of Jesus shall indeed <hi>feast</hi> with him at the <hi>great Supper,</hi> but some shall be placed nearer to him than others, and still there shall be a <hi>Beloved Disciple</hi> that shall <hi>lean</hi> on his <hi>Bosom.</hi> I know this Doctrine concerning different degrees of Glory, is (and indeed what is there that is not) very much question'd by some, and peremptorily deny'd by others; but since it is so highly agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the goodness and bounty of God, and to the <hi>Catholic</hi> Measures of Sense and Reason; and is so mightily favour'd, if not expresly asserted in many places of Scripture, I shall not here go about to establish the truth of it, but taking it for granted, do urge this as another consideration of great moment, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward encouraging the practice of <hi>Heroic Piety.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, and lastly, I consider, that We have indeed but very little time to serve God in. The Life of man at longest is but
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49931:43"/>short, and considering how small a part of it we <hi>live,</hi> much <hi>shorter.</hi> If we <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> from the <hi>Computation</hi> of our Years (as we must do, if we will take a true estimate of our Life) that part of our time which is spent in the incogitancy of Infancy and Childhood, the impertinence and heedlesness of Youth, in the necessities of Nature, Eating, Drinking, Sleeping, and other Refreshments; in business and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Concerns, engagements with Friends and Relations, in the offices of Civility and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual intercourse; besides a thousand other unnecessary avocations: we shall find that there is but a small portion left even for the Retirements of Study, for our improvement in Arts and Sciences, and other intellectual accomplishments. But then if we consider what great <hi>disbursements</hi> of our time are made upon <hi>them</hi> also, we shall find that Religion is <hi>crowded</hi> up into a very <hi>narrow compass;</hi> so narrow, that were not the rewards of Heaven matter of <hi>express Revelation,</hi> 'twould be the greatest <hi>Presumption</hi> imaginable to hope for them upon the condition of such <hi>inconsiderable</hi> Services. Since then our time of serving God is so very short, so infinitely
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49931:44"/>disproportionate to the rewards we expect from him, 'tis but a reasonable piece of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity to work <hi>with all our might,</hi> and do as much in it as we can: to supply the <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty</hi> of Time by <hi>frugal</hi> management and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenseness</hi> of affection, to serve God <hi>earnestly, vigorously,</hi> and <hi>zealously;</hi> and in one days Devotion to <hi>abbreviate</hi> the <hi>ordinary</hi> Piety of <hi>many years.</hi> 'Tis said of the Devil, that he prosecuted his malicious designs against the Church with greater earnestness and vigour,
<note place="margin">Revel. 12.12.</note> because <hi>he knew he had but a short time.</hi> And shall not the same consideration prevail with a <hi>generous</hi> Soul to do as much for God and Religion, as the Devil did <hi>against</hi> them? 'Tis a shame for him that has but a <hi>short</hi> part to act upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> not to perform it <hi>well,</hi> especially when he is to act it but <hi>once.</hi> Man has but one <hi>state of Probation,</hi> and that of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding short continuance, and therefore, since he cannot serve God <hi>long,</hi> he should serve him <hi>much,</hi> employ every minute of his life to the best advantage, <hi>thicken</hi> his Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>hallow</hi> every <hi>day</hi> in his <hi>Kalendar</hi> by Religious exercises, and every <hi>action</hi> in his <hi>Life</hi> by holy <hi>references</hi> and <hi>designments;</hi> for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49931:44"/>let him make what haste he can to be <hi>wise,</hi> Time will <hi>out-run</hi> him. This is a Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of infinite moment to him that duly weighs it; and he that <hi>thus numbers his days,</hi> will find great reason to <hi>apply his heart to</hi> more than <hi>ordinary</hi> degrees of <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:45"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:45"/>
                  <head>AN IDEA OF HAPPINESS, IN A LETTER to a FRIEND: ENQUIRING Wherein the Greatest Happiness attainable by Man in this Life does consist.</head>
                  <p>By <hi>JOHN NORRIS,</hi> Fellow of <hi>All-Souls</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Sollicitis vitam consumimus annis,</l>
                     <l>Torquemurque metu caecaque cupidine rerum,</l>
                     <l>Aeternisque Senes curis dum quaerimus aevum,</l>
                     <l>Perdimus, &amp; nullo votorum fine beati,</l>
                     <l>Victuros agimus semper, nec vivimus unquam.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Manilius lib. 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Norris,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1684.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:46"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:46"/>
                  <head>Ʋpon a Treatise called <hi>The Idea of Happiness.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>SOme</hi> Truths <hi>there are of so</hi> refin'd <hi>a strain,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They all</hi> Commerce <hi>with</hi> vulgar <hi>Souls dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> nobler <hi>Spirits only entertain;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who, while the Sordid Croud feed gross</hi> beneath,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Purer Element</hi> exalted <hi>breath.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To such alone our</hi> Author <hi>does prepare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>An</hi> Intellectual Treat <hi>of</hi> Heavenly <hi>fare;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rich</hi> Manna, <hi>true</hi> Elixir, <hi>drawn with art</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>More exquisite than</hi> Hermes <hi>could impart;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Substantial Happiness, <hi>Joys</hi> uncreate,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beyond the reach of Time, beyond the power of fate;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Foretasts <hi>of Bliss which in this life commence</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To the pure Intellect,</hi> abstract <hi>from sense;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such</hi> Extasies <hi>as raise the human Soul,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In</hi> trance inessable, <hi>above the Starry Pole;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ʋniting, Man by ways not understood,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To God, the</hi> universal Spring <hi>of Good.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great</hi> Mystery! <hi>which tho it soars above</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My groveling Reason, I</hi> adore <hi>and</hi> love.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Blest Ʋnion, which mankind</hi> advances <hi>more</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Than by the</hi> Fall <hi>it was</hi> debas'd <hi>before.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Man was at first</hi> below <hi>the</hi> Angels <hi>made,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But now with</hi> higher <hi>Glory is array'd.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49931:47"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They for their Errours found no offer'd Grace,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ever</hi> banish'd <hi>from their Makers Face.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But God himself in</hi> Human <hi>Form descends,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And man's</hi> Redemption <hi>by his Death</hi> commends.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By which vast Merit</hi> happy we <hi>receive</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Both</hi> in <hi>and</hi> with <hi>the Deity to Live.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who that his Dignity did truely know,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Would fix his fond desires on things below?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All the</hi> huge Boast <hi>of Life is but a Dream</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Compar'd with even a</hi> thought <hi>of</hi> this <hi>high Theme,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> great Idea, <hi>which so nobly Shines</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In the</hi> rich <hi>habit of</hi> thy wondrous <hi>Lines.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Farewell vain World, and all thy empty Pride,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With which it</hi> glitters <hi>only till 'tis</hi> try'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When the false Lustre vanishing away</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> baseness <hi>of the</hi> Metal <hi>does</hi> betray.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For I, directed by thy</hi> light Divine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To true and lasting Joys my Soul</hi> resign,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which here on Earth begin in less</hi> degree,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> higher <hi>run to all</hi> Eternity.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>London, <date>Feb. 12. 1684.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>G. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:47"/>
                  <head>To the admir'd (though to me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known) Author, on his ingenious Treatise, <hi>The Idea of Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>SOme</hi> Ages <hi>of the World had pass'd, before</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our Fathers found the use of</hi> Sail <hi>and</hi> Oar.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Enthark'd securely in a hollow Tree,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They</hi> rudely <hi>ventur'd first to</hi> Plough <hi>the Sea.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With Branches they suppli'd the use of Oar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their</hi> Rule <hi>and</hi> Compass <hi>was the</hi> adjacent <hi>Shore.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But still</hi> Experience <hi>taught them, and they grew</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Both</hi> Wiser <hi>every day, and</hi> Bolder too.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And every Generation found out something</hi> new.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At length by sume</hi> Great Hero <hi>was made known,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To men, the</hi> Art <hi>of</hi> Navigation.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And now in</hi> foreign <hi>Goods the Merchants trade,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Islands <hi>begin to be inhabited.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But still their Knowledge did</hi> contracted <hi>lye</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In</hi> little <hi>room, lame was their</hi> Geography,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And to affirm</hi> Antipodes <hi>was</hi> Heresie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till the</hi> Great Drake <hi>resolv'd the</hi> weighty <hi>doubt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By compassing the spatious World about.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The mighty</hi> Drake, <hi>who Regions did explore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Known only to</hi> One <hi>greater</hi> Traveller, <hi>the Sun, before.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49931:48"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So we had never seen the brightest ray</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Truth Divine, <hi>hadst thou not shewn the way.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou art our</hi> Drake, <hi>Thou who alone didst dare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To move in an</hi> unknown, untrodden <hi>Sphere,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, for</hi> less active <hi>Mortals, didst descry</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>New <hi>Worlds of most refin'd</hi> Philosophy.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So, by the Conduct of an</hi> Angel<hi>'s Hand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Israelites possess'd the</hi> happy Land.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To thee, on</hi> Contemplation's Mount, <hi>were shewn</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Heavenly</hi> Glories, <hi>on the</hi> Face <hi>they</hi> shone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And with thee thou hast brought the</hi> inherent <hi>Brightness down.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In thy</hi> Idea <hi>we</hi> ingraven <hi>see,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In</hi> Characters <hi>Divine,</hi> Felicity.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou a</hi> new <hi>Map of</hi> paradise <hi>hast drawn,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And more</hi> exact <hi>than er'e before was known.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which (if there's ought that</hi> Poets <hi>may foretell)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall last as long ('tis drawn so rarely well</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As men</hi> believe <hi>a Heaven, or</hi> fear <hi>a Hell.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>London, <date>Feb. 7. 1684.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>W. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:48"/>
                  <head>ON Mr. <hi>Norris</hi>'s Idea of Happiness.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>WHEN our</hi> inspired <hi>Writer, mounting on</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Wings <hi>of</hi> tow'ring Contemplation,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Could not to our</hi> low Sphere <hi>his flight confine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But with a Genius Divine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Flew high, and</hi> Cut <hi>the pure Aetherial</hi> Line;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When all dissolv'd in Extasies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He his</hi> Idea <hi>fram'd of</hi> Happiness;</l>
                     <l>A <hi>bright fac'd</hi> Cherub <hi>'twas that led the way,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And clear'd his Eyes with a Caelestial Ray,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And that he might to men make known</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His strange</hi> Mysterious Revelation,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inspir'd his Soul with</hi> Gusts <hi>and</hi> Strains <hi>Divine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beyond whate're were given by the</hi> Sacred Nine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With him he took his flight</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Through the vast Orbs of Light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Left all our gilded Toys,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our</hi> Atmosphere <hi>of</hi> dusky <hi>Joys,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No false disguises could his Eyes betray</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nor gaudy</hi> Lures <hi>his flight delay,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Towards Heaven he made, and everlasting Day.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:49"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Seraphins <hi>they guarded him along,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And as he upwards did aspire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With</hi> Hallelujahs <hi>rais'd his</hi> Genius <hi>higher,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And with</hi> Coelestial Cadence <hi>fill'd his Tongue.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till he at length pass'd on,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Through many a Blissful Region,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To the bright</hi> Court <hi>above,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Element <hi>of</hi> Love.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where, with enlightned and inamour'd Eyes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In Beatific extasies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He view'd the dazling</hi> Jasper <hi>mound</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That did the</hi> Empyrean <hi>Seat surround,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The great</hi> Metropolis <hi>of Bliss,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And in its</hi> Anti-courts <hi>did sit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Enjoying all that could be fit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For one not made Immortal yet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus did his Soul from Heaven but one remove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Abstracted by Seraphic Love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From tyes Corporeal well nigh rent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By powerfull</hi> Energys <hi>of Thought intent</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dwell fix'd in</hi> Contemplation <hi>on the bright</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ideas <hi>of the God of Light.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till scorning sensual Objects, he could</hi> feast</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>On</hi> Praises, <hi>and on</hi> Anthems <hi>make</hi> Repast.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And did on this side Heaven with rays Divin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of antedated and immortal Glory Shine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:49"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then, like a</hi> bright Columbus, <hi>down the Skies</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He sail'd, his Voyage told, and</hi> new <hi>discoveries</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Islands</hi> Fortunate, <hi>and</hi> Coasts <hi>of Bliss</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Continents <hi>of</hi> everlasting <hi>Happiness.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And of them Charts and Maps he drew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fair, <hi>like th' Original, and</hi> True,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Casting the</hi> Rumb<hi>'s by w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> you are to Steer,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And how the Shelves to pass, and how the Rocks to clear</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Joys that</hi> true <hi>and</hi> good <hi>appear.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He tells how the Coast</hi> bears, <hi>and how to</hi> tack</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lest we for</hi> Shoar <hi>the</hi> Clouds <hi>mistake,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lest into</hi> gulphs <hi>of</hi> sensual <hi>Joys we fall</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pursuing</hi> Intellectual;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He shews the shortness of the formers date,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How</hi> few <hi>they are, and how they</hi> Circulate</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Still to the</hi> Point <hi>from whence they first begun,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That nothing's</hi> good <hi>nor</hi> new <hi>under the</hi> Sun.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then, as a Radient</hi> Cynosure, <hi>he leads</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By these his Lines of Light</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And paths then</hi> Milky <hi>way more bright,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Souls more refin'd; Them he conducts and guides,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By many a</hi> Degree</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of the large</hi> Latitude <hi>of Extasie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In th' Ocean of perpetual delight</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49931:50"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Through Visions, Raptures, Elevations high,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To the</hi> round <hi>Haven of Eternity.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till by Calm</hi> Silence <hi>all a round</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And still tranquillity 'tis found</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That an eternal</hi> Paradise <hi>is</hi> nigh.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And having made the</hi> Port</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where joys without allay resort,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They take their</hi> larger <hi>Portions with the Blest</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In</hi> Vision, Love, <hi>and</hi> Joy, <hi>and endless</hi> Rest.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>London, <date>March 25. 1684.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>S. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49931:50"/>
                  <head>An Idea of Happiness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THO you have been pleas'd to assign me the Task of an Angel, and in that Respect have warranted me to disobey you; yet since, a considerable part of that experimental Knowledge which I have of Happiness is owing to the Delight which I take in your vertuous and endearing Friendship, I think 'tis but reasonable I should endeavour to give you an <hi>Idea</hi> of that, whereof you have given me the <hi>Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You desire to know of me wherein the greatest Happiness attainable by man in this Life does consist. And here, tho I see my self engaged in a work already too difficult for me, yet I find it necessary to enlarge it: For, since the greatest Happiness, or <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Bonum</hi> of this Life is a <hi>Species</hi> of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness in general, and since it is call'd (Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est) not because absolutely perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat; but inasmuch as it comes nearest to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49931:51"/>that which indeed is so, it will be necessary first to state the Notion of Happiness in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and then to define wherein that Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness does consist which is perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, before I can proceed to a Resolution of your Question.</p>
                  <p>By Happiness, in the most general Sense of the word, I understand nothing else but an Enjoyment of any Good. The least Degree of Good has the same Proportion to the least Degree of Happiness as the greatest has to the greatest, and consequently as many ways as a man enjoys any Good, so many ways he may be said to be happy: neither will the Mixture of Evil make him forfeit his Right to this Title, unless it either <hi>equals</hi> the Good he enjoys, or <hi>exceeds</hi> it: And then indeed it does; but the Reason is, because in strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Speaking, upon the whole Account the man enjoys no Good at all: For if the Good and the Evil be equal-balanc'd, it must needs be indifferent to that man either to be or not to be, there being not the least <hi>Grain</hi> of good to determine his Choice: So that he can no more be said to be happy in that Condition, than he could before he was born. And much less, if the Evil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the Good: For then he is not only
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49931:51"/>not happy, but absolutely and purely mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: For after an exact Commensuration supposed between the Good and the Evil, all that remains over of the Evil is pure and simple Misery; which is the Case of the Damn'd: And when 'tis once come to this (whatever some Mens <hi>Metaphysicks</hi> may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade them) I am very well satisfied, that 'tis better not to be than to be. But now on the other side, if the Good does never so little out-weigh the Evil, that <hi>Overplus</hi> of Good is as pure and unallay'd in its Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if there were no such Mixture at all; and consequently the Possession of it may properly be call'd Happiness.</p>
                  <p>I know the Masters of Moral Philosophy do not treat of Happiness in this Latitude; neither is it fit they should: For their Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness being to point out the ultimate End of Humane Actions, it would be an impertinent thing for them to give any other <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Happiness</hi> than the highest: But however this does not hinder but that the General <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Happiness</hi> may be extended farther, even to the Fruition of any Good whatsoever: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any reason to find Fault with the Latitude of this Notion, since we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Degrees even in Glory.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49931:52"/>
                  <p>In this General <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Happiness</hi> two things are contain'd. One is, some Good, either real of apparent, in the Fruition of which we are said to be in some measure or other happy. The other is the very Fruition it self. The first of these is usually called <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective Happiness,</hi> and the latter <hi>Formal.</hi> Some I know divide Happiness into these as distinct <hi>Species;</hi> but I think not so artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally: For they are both but constituent Parts, which joyntly make up one and the same Happiness: Neither of them are suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent alone, but they are both equally neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary. That the last of these is a necessary Ingredient, I think no doubt can reasonably be made: For what would the greatest Good imaginable signifie without Fruition? And that the former is likewise necessary is no less certain: For how can there be such a thing as Fruition without an Object? I grant 'tis not at all necessary that the Object be a real substantial Good; if it appear so, 'tis sufficient.</p>
                  <p>From this Distinction of <hi>real</hi> and <hi>apparent</hi> Good, some have taken occasion to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish of Happiness likewise into two sorts, <hi>real</hi> and <hi>imaginary:</hi> But I believe, upon a more narrow Scrutiny into the matter, 'twill
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49931:52"/>be found, that all Happiness, according to its Proportion, is equally <hi>real;</hi> and that that which they term <hi>Imaginary,</hi> too w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves the Name, there being no such thing in Nature: For let the Object of it be never so <hi>Phantastick,</hi> yet it must still carry the Semblance and Appearance of Good (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise it can neither <hi>move</hi> the Appetite nor please it, and consequently be neither an Object of <hi>Desire</hi> nor of <hi>Fruition;</hi>) and if so, the Happiness must needs be real, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Formality of the Object, thō 'twere never so true and real good, would notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing lie in the <hi>Appearance,</hi> not in the <hi>Reality:</hi> Whether it be real or no is purely accidental: For, since to be happy can be nothing else but to enjoy something which I desire, the Object of my Happiness must needs be <hi>enjoy'd</hi> under the same Formality as 'tis <hi>desired.</hi> Now since 'tis desired only as apparently good, it must needs please me when obtained under the same Notion. So that it matters not to the Reality of my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, whether the Object of it be really good, or only apprehended so, since if it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so <hi>real,</hi> it <hi>pleases</hi> only as <hi>apparent.</hi> The Fool has his Paradice as well as the Wise-man, and for the time is as happy in it; and a kind
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49931:53"/>Delusion will make a Cloud as pleasing as the Queen of <hi>Heaven.</hi> And therefore I think it impossible for a man to think himself hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and (during that Perswasion) not really to be so. He enjoys the <hi>Creature</hi> of his own Fancy, worships the <hi>Idol</hi> of his Imagination, and the happiest man upon Earth does no more: For let the Circumstances of his Life be what they will, 'tis his Opinion only that must give the Relish. Without this, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it self would afford him no Content, nor the Vision of God prove <hi>Beatific.</hi> 'Tis true, the man is seated at the <hi>Spring-Head</hi> of Happiness, is surrounded with excellent Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; but alas, it appears not so to him; he is not at all affected with his Condition, but, like <hi>Adam,</hi> lies fast in a dead Sleep in the midst of Paradice.</p>
                  <p>The Sum of this Argument is this; Good is in the same manner the Object of <hi>Fruition,</hi> as 'tis of Desire; and that is not as <hi>really</hi> good in its own Nature, but as 'tis <hi>judged</hi> so by the Understanding: And consequently, tho it be only apparent, it must needs be as effectual to <hi>gratifie</hi> the Appetite as it was at first to <hi>excite</hi> it during that Appearance. So long as it keeps on its Vizor and imposes upon the Understanding, what is wanting in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49931:53"/>the thing, is made up by an <hi>obliging</hi> Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, and <hi>Ignorance</hi> becomes here the Mother of <hi>Happiness</hi> as well as of <hi>Devotion:</hi> But if the man will <hi>dare</hi> to be wise, and too curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously examine the superficial Tinsel-Good, he undeceives himself to his own Cost, and, like <hi>Adam,</hi> adventuring to eat of the Tree of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> sees himself naked, and is ashamed. And for this reason I think it impossible for any man to love to be flatter'd: 'Tis true, he may delight to hear himself com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by those who indeed do flatter him; but the true reason of that is, because he does not apprehend that to be Flattery which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is so; but when he once throughly knows it, 'tis impossible he should be any longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with it. I shall conclude this Point with this useful Reflection, That since every Man's Happiness depends wholly upon his own Opinion, the Foundation upon which all envious Men proceed, must needs be either <hi>false</hi> or very <hi>uncertain.</hi> False, if they think that outward Circumstances and States of Life are all the Ingredients of Happiness; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain however: For since they measure the Happiness of other Men by their own Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 'tis mere Chance if they do not misplace their Envy, unless they were sure the other
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49931:54"/>Person was of the like Opinion with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. And now what a vain irrational thing is it to disquiet our selves into a dislike of our own Condition, merely because we mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake another Man's?</p>
                  <p>Thus far of the Notion of Happiness in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; I now proceed to consider that Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness which is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (as <hi>Plato</hi> speaks) sound and entire, perfect and compleat. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the general Notion of which, all men, I suppose, are as much agreed as they are in the <hi>Idea</hi> of a <hi>Priangle.</hi> That 'tis such a State than which a better cannot be conceiv'd: In which there is no Evil you can fear, no Good which you desire and have not; That which fully and constantly satisfies the Demand of every Appetite, and leaves no possibility for a desire of Change; or to summ it up in that comprehensive Expression of the Poet,
<q>Quod sis esse velis, nihilque malis.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>When you would always be what you are, and (as the Earl of <hi>Roscommond</hi> very signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantly renders it) do <hi>Rather</hi> nothing. This I suppose is the utmost that can be said or conceiv'd of it, and less than this will not be enough. And thus far we are all agreed. For I suppose, the many various Disputes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49931:54"/>maintained by Philosophers concerning Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, could not respect this general Notion of it, but only the particular <hi>causes</hi> or <hi>means</hi> whereby it might be acquired. And I find <hi>Tully</hi> concurring with me in the same Observation,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Fin.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Ea est beata vita</hi> (says he) <hi>quaerimus autem non quae fit, sed unde.</hi> The difficulty is not to frame a conception of a perfectly happy State in the general, but to define in particular wherein it consists.</p>
                  <p>But before I undertake this Province, I think it might not be amiss to remove one Prejudice, which, because it has gain'd upon my self sometimes in my Melancholy Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I am apt to think it may be incident to other men also. It is this, Whether af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so many Desputes about, so many rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less endeavours after this state of perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, there be any such thing or no. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not a meer <hi>Idea,</hi> as imaginary as <hi>Plato</hi>'s <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as fictious as the Groves of <hi>Elysium.</hi> I confess, this suspicion has often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>overcast</hi> my mind with black thoughts, damp'd my Devotion, and as it were, clipp'd the Wings of my Aspiring Soul. And I hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to fall into it upon a serious reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the nature of Fruition in the several Periods and Circumstances of my Life. For
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49931:55"/>I observ'd according to my <hi>Narrow</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that I never had in all my Life the same thoughts of any good in the very time of the enjoying it as I had before. I have known when I have promised my self vast Satisfactions, and my imagination has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented me at a distance with a fair <hi>Landscape</hi> of Delights, yet when I drew nigh to grasp the alluring Happiness, like the <hi>Sensitive Plant</hi> it contracted it self at the <hi>touch,</hi> and <hi>shrink'd</hi> almost to nothing in the Fruition. And though after the Enjoyment is past, it seems great again upon <hi>Reflection</hi> as it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Expectation,</hi> yet should a <hi>Platonical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution</hi> make the same Circumstances recur, I should not think so. I found 'twas ever with me as with the <hi>Traveller,</hi> to whom the Ground which is before him, and that which he has left <hi>behind</hi> him seems always more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously embroider'd and delightsome, than that which he <hi>stands</hi> upon. So that my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, like the time wherein I <hi>thought</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, was always either <hi>past</hi> or to <hi>come,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>present.</hi> Methought I could often say upon a <hi>Recollection,</hi> How happy <hi>was</hi> I at such a time! Or when I was in <hi>expectation.</hi> How happy <hi>shall</hi> I be if I compass such a design! But scarce ever, I <hi>am</hi> so. I was pretty well
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49931:55"/>pleas'd methought while I expected, while I hoped, till Fruition jogg'd me out of my pleasing slumber and I knew it was but a Dream. And this single Consideration has often made me even in the very pursuit after Happiness, and full career of my Passions, to stop short on this side of Fruition, and to choose rather with <hi>Moses</hi> upon Mount <hi>Nebo</hi> to entertain my fancy with a remote Prospect of the <hi>Happy Land,</hi> than to go in and Possess it, and then <hi>Repine.</hi> How then shall Man be happy, when setting aside all the Crosses of Fortune, he will complain even of <hi>Success,</hi> and <hi>Fruition</hi> it self shall <hi>disappoint</hi> him!</p>
                  <p>And this melancholy reflection bred in me a kind of Suspicion, that for all that I knew it might be so in <hi>Heaven</hi> too. That although at this distance I might frame to my self bright <hi>Ideas</hi> of that Region of Bliss; yet when I came to the Possession of it, I should not find that perfect Happiness there which I expected, but that it would be always to <hi>come</hi> as 'tis now, and that I should seek for Heaven even in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it self. That I should not fully acquiesce in my condition there, but at length desire a Change. And that which confirm'd me the more in this <hi>unhappy Scepticism,</hi> was, because I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd that a great number of excellent Beings
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49931:56"/>who enjoyed the very <hi>Quintessence</hi> of Bliss, who were as happy as God and Heaven could make them, grew soon uneasy and weary of their State and <hi>left their own Habitation.</hi> Which argues that their Happiness was not <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>compleat,</hi> because otherwise they would not have <hi>desired</hi> a Change, since that very desire is an Imperfection. And if Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness be not compleat in Heaven, sure 'tis impossible to be found any where else.</p>
                  <p>Before therefore I proceed to define where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in perfect Happiness does consist, I think it necessary to endeavour the removal of this Scruple, which, like the flaming Sword, forbids <hi>entrance</hi> into <hi>Paradice.</hi> In order to which, I shall inquire into the <hi>true Reason</hi> why these Sublunary good things when enjoyed do <hi>neither</hi> answer our <hi>expectations,</hi> nor satisfy our <hi>Appetites.</hi> Now this must <hi>proceed either</hi> from the nature of Fruition it self, or from the Imperfection of it, or from the Object of it, or from our selves. I confess, did this <hi>defect</hi> proceed from the <hi>very nature</hi> of Fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as is supposed in the Objection) 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible there should be any such thing as <hi>perfect Happiness,</hi> since 'twould <hi>faint</hi> away while <hi>enjoy'd,</hi> and <hi>expire</hi> in our <hi>embraces.</hi> But that it cannot proceed thence, I have this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49931:56"/>to offer, Because Fruition being nothing else but an Application or Union of the Soul to some good or agreeable Object, it is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that should <hi>lessen</hi> the <hi>good</hi> enjoyed. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> it may lessen our <hi>estimation</hi> of it, but that is because we do not rightly consider the nature of things, but promise our <hi>selves</hi> infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Satisfactions in the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of finite Objects. We look upon things through a false Glass, which Magnifies the Object at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance much beyond its just Dimensions. We represent our <hi>future enjoyments</hi> to our selves in such <hi>savourable</hi> and <hi>partial Ideas</hi> which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract from all the <hi>inconveniencies</hi> and allays which will really in the <hi>Event</hi> accompany them. And if we thus over-rate our <hi>Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> before-hand, 'tis no wonder if they baulk our <hi>Expectations</hi> in the <hi>Fruition.</hi> But then it must be observed, that the <hi>Fruition</hi> does not <hi>cause</hi> this <hi>Deficiency</hi> in the Object, but only <hi>discover</hi> it. We have a better insight into the Nature of things near at hand, than when we stood afar off, and consequently discern those <hi>defects</hi> and <hi>imperfections,</hi> which, like the qualities of an ill Mistriss, lay hid all the time of <hi>Courtship,</hi> and now begin to betray them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, when 'tis come to <hi>enjoyment.</hi> But this can never happen but where the Object is finite. An
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49931:57"/>infinite Object can never be over-valued and consequently cannot frustrate our <hi>Expectations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as we are not to charge <hi>Fruition</hi> with our <hi>disappointments</hi> but our selves (because we are accessory to our own <hi>delusion</hi> by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king false measures of things) so neither is the <hi>Ʋnsatisfactoriness</hi> of any condition to be imputed to the Nature of <hi>Fruition</hi> it self, but either to the <hi>imperfection</hi> of it or to the finiteness of the Object. Let the Object be never so perfect, yet if the <hi>Fruition</hi> of it be in an imperfect measure there will still be room for <hi>Ʋnsatisfactoriness,</hi> as it appears in our <hi>enjoyment</hi> of God in this Life. Neither can a <hi>finite Object</hi> fully satisfy us though we enjoy it never so thoroughly. For since to a full satisfaction and <hi>acquiescence</hi> of Mind 'tis required that our Faculties be always <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> and we ever <hi>enjoying:</hi> it is impossible a <hi>finite Object</hi> should afford this Satisfaction, because all the good that is in it (being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite) is at length run over, and then the <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment</hi> is at an end, The flower is suck'd dry, and we necessarily desire a Change. Whenever therefore our <hi>enjoyment</hi> proves unsatisfying, we may conclude, that either the Object is <hi>finite,</hi> or the <hi>Fruition</hi> imperfect. But then how came the <hi>Angels</hi> to be dissatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49931:57"/>with their Condition in the Regions of <hi>light</hi> and <hi>immortality,</hi> when they drank free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Fountain of Life</hi> proceeding out of the Throne of God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Revel.</hi> 26.</note> with whom is fulness of Joy, and at whose Right hand are <hi>Pleasures for evermore.</hi> Here certainly there is no room either for the <hi>finiteness</hi> of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or the <hi>imperfection</hi> of <hi>Fruition.</hi> And therefore their dissatisfaction can be imputed to no other Cause, than the Nature of <hi>Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in general, which is to <hi>lessen</hi> the good <hi>enjoyed,</hi> as was supposed in the <hi>Objection.</hi> This I confess presses hard, and indeed, I have but one way to <hi>extricate</hi> my self from this difficulty, and that is by supposing a <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Probation</hi> in the <hi>Angels.</hi> That they did not immediately upon their <hi>Creation</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy an <hi>infinite Object,</hi> or if they did, yet that 'twas in an <hi>imperfect measure.</hi> For should it be granted that they were at first confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Bliss and <hi>compleatly happy</hi> both in <hi>respect</hi> of <hi>Fruition</hi> and <hi>Object,</hi> as we suppose they are now, I cannot <hi>conceive</hi> it possible they should be dissatisfy'd with their Condition. This being repugnant to the <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Since then this dissatisfaction must be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived either from the imperfection of the <hi>Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49931:58"/>or the finiteness of the Object, and not from the Nature of Fruition in the general, to infer the possibility of perfect <hi>Happiness,</hi> there needs no more to be supposed than the <hi>existence</hi> of a Being full fraught with infinite inexhaustable good, and that he is able to Communicate to the full. There may be then such a thing as Perfect <hi>Happiness.</hi> The possibility of which may also be further <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> (tho not <hi>explicated</hi>) from those bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Desires, that <hi>immortal Thirst</hi> every man has after it by Nature: Concerning which I observe, that nothing does more constantly, more inseparably cleave to our Minds than this Desire of perfect and consummated Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness: This, as <hi>Plato</hi> pathetically expresses it, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the most excellent end of all our Endeavours, the great Prize, the great Hope. This is the Mark every Man shoots at, and tho we miss our Aim never so often, yet we will not, cannot give over; but, like passionate Lovers, take <hi>Resolution</hi> from a <hi>Repulse.</hi> The rest of our Passions are much at our own Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal; yield either to Reason or Time; we either Argue our selves out of them, or at least out-live them. We are not always in Love with Pomp and Grandeur, nor always
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49931:58"/>dazzled with the glittering of Riches; and there is a Season when Pleasure it self shall Court in vain: But the desire of perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness has no Intervals, no Vicissitudes, it out-lasts the Motion of the Pulse, and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives the Ruins of the Grave. <hi>Many VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot quench it, neither can the Floods Drown it:</hi> And now certainly God would never have planted such an Ardent, such an importunate Appetite in our Souls, and as it were <hi>interwoven</hi> it with our very Natures, had he not been able to satisfie it.</p>
                  <p>I come now to shew wherein this perfect Happiness does consist, concerning which, I affirm in the first place, that it is not to be found in any thing we can enjoy in this Life. The greatest Fruition we have of God here, is imperfect, and consequently unsatisfactory. And as for all other Objects they are finite, and consequently, though never so fully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd, cannot afford us perfect Satisfaction. No;
<note place="margin">Job 28.</note>
                     <hi>Man knoweth not the price there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Neither is it to be found in the Land of the Living. The Depth saith, it is not in me, and the Sea saith, it is not in me.</hi> The Vanity of the Creature has been so co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piously discoursed upon, both by Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and Divines, and is withall so obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49931:59"/>to every thinking man's <hi>Experience,</hi> that I need not here take an <hi>Inventory</hi> of the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> nor turn <hi>Ecclesiastes</hi> after <hi>Solomon.</hi> And besides, I have already anticipated this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in what I have said concerning <hi>Fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> I shall only add one or two Remarks concerning the Objects of <hi>Secular Happiness,</hi> which are not so commonly insisted upon, to what has been there said. The first is this, that the Objects wherein Men generally seek for <hi>Happiness</hi> here, are not only <hi>finite</hi> in their <hi>Nature,</hi> but also <hi>few</hi> in <hi>number.</hi> Indeed, could a Man's Life be so contrived, that he should have a new <hi>Pleasure</hi> still ready at hand assoon as <hi>he</hi> was grown <hi>weary</hi> of the Old, and <hi>every</hi> day <hi>enjoy a Virgin</hi> Delight, he might then perhaps like Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for a while think himself happy in this <hi>continued Succession of new Acquisitions.</hi> But alas, Nature does not treat us with this Variety. The compass of our <hi>enjoyments</hi> is much shorter than that of our Lives, and there is a <hi>Periodical Circulation</hi> of our <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures</hi> as well as of our <hi>Blood.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>—Versamur ibidem atque insumus usque.</l>
                        <l>Nec nova vivendo procuditur ulla voluptas.</l>
                     </q>
                     <bibl>Lucretius.</bibl>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49931:59"/>The Enjoyments of our Lives run in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Round like the Months in the <hi>Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> but with a quicker Revolution; we <hi>dance</hi> like <hi>Fairies</hi> in a <hi>Circle,</hi> and our whole Life is but a nauseous <hi>Tautology:</hi> We rise like the Sun, and run the same Course we did the day before, and to morrow is but the same over again: So that the greatest Favourite of Fortune will have Reason often enough to cry out with him in <hi>Seneca, Quosque eadem?</hi> But there is another Grievance which contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to defeat our Endeavours after perfect Happiness in the Enjoyments of this Life; Which is, that the Objects wherein we seek it, are not only <hi>finite</hi> and <hi>few;</hi> but that they commonly prove Occasions of greater <hi>Sorrow</hi> to us than ever they afforded us <hi>Content.</hi> This may be made out several ways, as from the Labour of Getting, the Care of Keeping, the fear of Losing, and the like Topicks, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly insisted on by others; but I wave these, and fix upon another Account less blown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and I think more material than any of the rest. It is this, that altho the Object lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses that great appearance in the <hi>Fruition</hi> which it had in the <hi>expectation,</hi> yet after it is gone it Resumes it again. Now we, when we lament the loss, do not take our measures
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49931:60"/>from that appearance which the Object had in the <hi>Enjoyment</hi> (as we should do to make our sorrow not exceed our <hi>Happiness</hi>) but from that which it has in the <hi>reflection,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently we must needs be more <hi>miserable</hi> in the loss then we were <hi>happy</hi> in the <hi>enjoyment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From these and the like <hi>Considerations,</hi> I think it will evidently appear, that this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Happiness</hi> is not to be found in any thing we can enjoy in this Life. Wherein then does it consist? I answer positively, in the full and entire Fruition of God. He (as <hi>Plato</hi> speaks) is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Proper and Principal End of Man, the Center of our <hi>Tendency,</hi> the Ark of our <hi>Rest.</hi> He is the Object which alone can satisfy the appetite of the most Capacious Soul, and stand the <hi>Test</hi> of Fruition to Eternity. And to enjoy him fully is perfect Felicity. This in general, is no more than what is deliver'd to us in Scripture, and was believ'd by many of the <hi>Heathen Philosophers.</hi> But the manner of this Fruition requires a more particular <hi>Consideration.</hi> Much is said by the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men upon this Subject, whereof, in the first place, I shall give a short and methodical ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and then fix upon the Opinion which I best approve of. The first thing that I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49931:60"/>is, that 'tis generally agreed upon among them, that this Fruition of God consists in some <hi>Operation;</hi> and I think with very good Reason. For as by the <hi>Objective</hi> part of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Happiness</hi> we understand that which is best and last, and to which all other things are to be referr'd; So by the <hi>Formal</hi> part of it must be understood the best and last Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitude of Man toward that best Object, so that the <hi>Happiness</hi> may both ways satisfy the Appetite, that is, as 'tis the best thing, and as 'tis the Possession, Use, or Fruition of that best thing: Now this habitude whereby the best thing is perfectly possess'd, must needs be some <hi>Operation,</hi> because <hi>Operation</hi> is the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate perfection of every Being. Which <hi>Axiom</hi> (as <hi>Cajetan</hi> well observes) must not be so understood as if Operation taken by it self were more perfect than the thing which tends to it, but that every thing with its Operation is more perfect than without it.</p>
                  <p>The next thing which I observe, is, that 'tis also farther agreed upon among them, that this Operation wherein our Fruition of God does consist, is an Operation of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual</hi> part, and not of the <hi>Sensitive.</hi> And this also I take to be very reasonable. First, because 'tis generally receiv'd, that the Essence of God cannot be the Object of any of our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49931:61"/>Senses. But Secondly, Suppose it could, yet since this Operation wherein our <hi>perfect Happiness</hi> does consist must be the perfectest Operation, and since that of the <hi>Intellectual</hi> part is more perfect than that of the <hi>Sensitive,</hi> it follows that the Operation whereby we enjoy God must be that of the <hi>Intellectual</hi> part only.</p>
                  <p>But now whereas the <hi>Intellectual</hi> part of man (as 'tis opposed to the <hi>Sensitive</hi>) is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>viz.</hi> That of the <hi>Ʋnderstanding,</hi> and that of the <hi>Will,</hi> there has commenced a great Controversy between the <hi>Thomists</hi> and the <hi>Scotists,</hi> in which Act or Operation of the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Soul</hi> the <hi>Fruition</hi> of God does consist, whether in an Act of the <hi>Ʋnderstanding,</hi> or in an Act of the <hi>Will.</hi> The <hi>Thomists</hi> will have it consist purely in an Act of the <hi>Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,</hi> which is <hi>Vision.</hi> The <hi>Scotists</hi> in Act of the <hi>Will,</hi> which is <hi>Love.</hi> I intend not here to launch out into those <hi>Voluminous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricacies</hi> and <hi>Abstrusities,</hi> occasioned by the management of this Argument: It may suffice to tell you, that I think they are both in the extream, and therefore I shall take the middle way and resolve the perfect Fruition of God partly into <hi>Vision</hi> and partly into <hi>Love.</hi> These are the two arms with which we embrace the Divinity, and unite our Souls to the <hi>fair</hi> one
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49931:61"/>and the <hi>good.</hi> These I conceive are both so <hi>essential</hi> to the <hi>perfect Fruition</hi> of God, that the <hi>Idea</hi> of it can by no means be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if either of them be wanting. For, <hi>since</hi> God is both Supream <hi>Truth</hi> and infinite <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> he cannot be intirely possess'd but by the most clear <hi>knowledge</hi> and the most ardent <hi>love.</hi> And besides, since the Soul is happy by her Faculties, her Happiness must consist in the most perfect Operation of each Faculty. For if Happiness did consist formally in the sole Operation of the <hi>Ʋnderstanding</hi> (as most say) or in the sole Operation of the <hi>Will</hi> (as others) the Man would not be compleatly and in all respects Happy. For how is it possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Man should be perfectly Happy in loving the greatest good if he did not know it, or in knowing it if he did not love it? And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, these two Operations do so mutually tend to the promotion and conservation of one another, that upon this depends the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity and the constancy of our Happiness. For while the Blessed do <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Face to Face contemplate the Supream Truth and the infinite Goodness, they cannot chuse but love perpetually; and while they perpetually love, they cannot chuse but perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualy contemplate. And in this mutual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49931:62"/>of the Actions of the Soul consists the <hi>perpetuity</hi> of Heaven, the <hi>Circle</hi> of Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
                  <p>Besides this way of resolving our <hi>fruition</hi> of God into <hi>Vision</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> there is a Famous Opinion said to be <hi>broacht</hi> by <hi>Henricus Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davensis,</hi> who, upon a Supposition that God could not be so fully enjoy'd as is required to perfect Happiness, only by the <hi>Operations</hi> or <hi>Powers</hi> of the Soul, fancied a certain <hi>Illapse</hi> whereby the <hi>Divine Essence</hi> did fall in with, and as it were penetrate the <hi>Essence</hi> of the Blessed. Which Opinion he endeavours to illustrate by this Similitude. That as a piece of Iron, red hot by reason of the <hi>Illapse</hi> of the fire into it, appears all over like fire, so the Souls of the Blessed by this <hi>Illapse</hi> of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Essence</hi> into them, shall be all over <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I think he has scarce any <hi>followers</hi> in this Opinion, but I am sure he had a <hi>leader.</hi> For this is no more than what <hi>Plato</hi> taught before him, as is to be seen in his Discourses about the <hi>refusion</hi> of the Souls of good men into the <hi>Anima Mundi,</hi> which is the self-same in other terms with this Opinion. And the Truth of what I affirm may farther appear from an expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that great <hi>Platonist Plotinus,</hi> (viz.) that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49931:62"/>
                     <hi>the Soul will then be Happy when it shall depart hence to God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Enn. 6. <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note>
                     <hi>and as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother and no longer her self shall become wholely his,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>having joyn'd her self to him as a Center to a Center.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That such an intimate <hi>Conjunction</hi> with God as is here described is possible, seems to me more than credible from the Nature of the <hi>Hypostatic</hi> Union, but whether our <hi>Fruition</hi> of God after this Life shall consist in it, none know but those happy Souls who enjoy him, and therefore I shall determine nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time. This only I observe, that should our <hi>Fruition</hi> of God consist in such an Union or rather <hi>Penetration</hi> of <hi>Essences,</hi> that would not exclude but rather infer those Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of <hi>Vision</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> as necessary to <hi>Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> but on the other hand, there seems no such necessity of this Union to the <hi>Fruition,</hi> but that it may be conceiv'd intire without it. And therefore why we should multiply diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties without cause, I see no reason. For my part I should think my self sufficiently happy in the clear, Vision of my Maker, nor should I desire any thing beyond the Prayer of <hi>Moses,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18.</note>
                     <hi>I beseech thee shew me thy Glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49931:63"/>
                  <p>For what an infinite Satisfaction, Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Delight must it needs be to have a clear and intimate perception of that Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Original Beauty, Perfection and Harmony, whereof all that appears fair and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent either to our <hi>Senses</hi> or <hi>Ʋnderstandings</hi> in this Life is but a faint imitation, a pale Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection! To see him who is the Fountain of all Being, containing in himself the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not only of all that is, but of all that is possible to be, <hi>the</hi> Alpha <hi>and</hi> Omega, <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and the ending, the first and the last, which is, and which was,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 1.8.</note>
                     <hi>and which is to come, the Almighty!</hi> To see him of whom all Nature is the <hi>Image,</hi> of whom all the Harmony both of the visible and invisible World is but the <hi>Eccho!</hi> To see him, who (as <hi>Plato</hi> divinely and magnificently expresses it) is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The immense Ocean of Beauty, which is it self by it self, with it self, uniform, alwayes existing! This certainly will affect the Soul with all the pleasing and ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing Transports of Love and Desire, Joy and Delight, Wonder and Amazement, together with a settled Acquiescence and Complacency of Spirit only less infinite than the <hi>Loveliness</hi> that causes it, and the peculiar Complacency of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49931:63"/>him who rejoyces in his own fulness, and the <hi>Comprehensions</hi> of Eternity. We see how strangely our Sense of <hi>Seeing</hi> is affected with the Harmony of <hi>Colours,</hi> and our sence of Hearing with the Harmony of Sounds, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that some have been too <hi>weak</hi> for the <hi>enjoyment,</hi> and have grown mad with the <hi>Sublimate</hi> of Pleasure. And if so, what then shall we think of the <hi>Beatific Vision,</hi> the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of which will so far transcend that of the other, as God who is all over Harmony and Proportion exceeds the sweetest Melody of Sounds and Colours, and the perception of the Mind is more vigorous, quick and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing than that of the Senses? This is <hi>perfect Happiness,</hi> this is the Tree of Life which grows in the <hi>midst</hi> of the <hi>Paradise</hi> of God, this is Heaven, which while the Learned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute about, the Good only enjoy. But I shall not venture to Soar any longer in these Heights, I find the <hi>Aether</hi> too thin here to breath in long, and the Brightness of the Region flash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es too strong upon my tender Sense; I shall therefore hasten to descend from the Mount of God, lest I grow <hi>giddy</hi> with speculation, and lose those Secrets which I have learnt there, the <hi>Cabala</hi> of Felicity.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49931:64"/>
                  <p>And now, (Sir) I come to consider your Question <hi>(viz.)</hi> Wherein the greatest Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness attainable by Man in this Life does consist. Concerning which, there is as great variety of Opinions among <hi>Philosophers,</hi> as there is among <hi>Geographers</hi> about the Seat of <hi>Paradise.</hi> The Learned <hi>Varro</hi> reckons up no less than 288 several Opinions about it, and yet notwithstanding the number of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters who have <hi>bequeath'd</hi> Volumes upon this Subject to Posterity, they seem to have been in the dark in nothing more than in this, and (excepting only a few <hi>Platonists,</hi> who placed Man's greatest End in the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Truth) they seem to have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken nothing so <hi>unhappily,</hi> as when they es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say'd to write of <hi>Happiness.</hi> Some measure their <hi>Happiness</hi> by the high-tide of their Riches, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did the Fertility of the Year by the increase of the River <hi>Nile.</hi> Others place it in the Pleasures of Sence, others in Honour and Greatness. But these and the like were Men of the common Herd, low groveling Souls, that either <hi>understood</hi> not the <hi>Dignity</hi> of Humane Nature, or else <hi>forgot</hi> that they were Men. But there were others of a <hi>Diviner Genius and Sublimer Spirit,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Queis meliore luto finxit praecordia Titan.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49931:64"/>
                  <p>Who had a more generous blood running in their Veins, which made them put a just value upon themselves, and scorn to place their greatest <hi>Happiness</hi> in that which they should blush to enjoy. And those were the <hi>Stoics</hi> and the <hi>Peripatetics,</hi> who both place the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>Happiness</hi> of this Life in the Actions of Vertue, with this only difference, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the former are contented with <hi>Naked Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> the latter require some other <hi>Collateral</hi> things to the farther <hi>accomplishment</hi> of <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness,</hi> such as are Health and Strength of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, a Competent Lively-hood, and the like.</p>
                  <p>And this Opinion has been subscribed to by the hands of eminent <hi>Moralists</hi> in all Ages. And as it is Venerable for its Antiquity, so has it gain'd no small Authority from the Pen of a great Modern Writer <hi>(Descartes)</hi> who resolves the greatest <hi>Happiness</hi> of this Life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right use of the <hi>Will,</hi> which consists in this, that a Man have a firm and constant purpose always to do that which he shall judge to be best.</p>
                  <p>I confess, the Practice of Vertue is a very great instrument of <hi>Happiness,</hi> and that there is a great deal more true satisfaction and solid content to be found in a constant course of well living, than in all the soft Caresses of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49931:65"/>the most <hi>studied</hi> Luxury, or the Voluptuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of a <hi>Seraglio.</hi> And therefore I have often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times been exceedingly pleased in the reading of a certain Passage in that Divine Moralist <hi>Hierocles,</hi> where he tells you, that the Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man lives much more pleasantly than the Vicious Man. <hi>For</hi> (says he) <hi>all Pleasure is the Companion of Action, it has no Subsistence of its own, but accompanies us in our doing such and such things. Hence 'tis that the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser Actions are accompanied with the meaner Pleasures. So that the good Man does not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excell the wicked Man in what is good, but has also the advantage of him even in Pleasure, for whose sake alone he is wicked. For he that chuses Pleasure with Filthiness, altho for a while he be sweetly and deliciously entertain'd, yet at last through the Filthiness, annexed to his Enjoyment, he is brought to a painful Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But now he that prefers Vertue with all her Labours and Difficulties, though at first for want of use it sits heavy upon him, yet by the Conjunction of good he alleviates the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and at last enjoys pure and unallay'd Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure with his Vertue. So that of necessity that Life is most unhappy, which is most wicked, and that most pleasant which is most vertuous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49931:65"/>
                  <p>Now this I readily submit to as a great truth, that the degrees of <hi>Happiness</hi> vary according to the degrees of <hi>Vertue,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that that Life which is most <hi>Vertuous</hi> is most <hi>Happy,</hi> with reference to those that are Vicious or less Vertuous, every degree of Vertue having a proportionate degree of <hi>Happiness</hi> accompanying it, (which is all, I suppose, that excellent Author intends.) But I do not think the most <hi>Vertuous</hi> Life <hi>so</hi> the most <hi>Happy,</hi> but that it may become Happier, unless something more be comprehended in the Word (Vertue) then the <hi>Stoics, Peripatetics,</hi> and the generality of other Moralists under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand by it. For with them it signifies no more but only such a firm <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or habitude of the Will to good, whereby we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly disposed, notwithstanding the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tendency of our Passions, to perform the necessary Offices of Life. This they call <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Vertue, and although this brings always <hi>Happiness</hi> enough with it to make am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple amends for all the difficulties which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the practise of it: Yet I am not of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that the greatest Happiness attainable by Man in this Life consists in it. But there is another and a higher Sense of the Word, which frequently occurs in the <hi>Pythagorean</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49931:66"/>and <hi>Platonic</hi> Writings, <hi>(viz.) Contemplation</hi> and the <hi>Ʋnitive</hi> way of Religion. And this they call <hi>Divine Vertue.</hi> I allow of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction, but I would not be thought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive it from the <hi>Principle,</hi> as if Moral Vertue were <hi>acquired,</hi> and this <hi>infused</hi> (for to speak ingeniously, infused Vertue seem'd ever to me as great a <hi>Paradox</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> as Occult qualities in <hi>Philosophy</hi>) but from the noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Object, the Object of the former being Moral good, and the Object of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God himself. The former is a State of <hi>Proficiency,</hi> the latter of <hi>Perfection.</hi> The former is a State of difficulty and contention, the latter of ease and serenity. The former is employ'd in mastering the Passions, and regulating the actions of common Life, the latter in Divine Meditation and the Extasies of <hi>Seraphic</hi> Love. He that has only the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, is like <hi>Moses</hi> with much difficulty climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to the Holy Mount, but he that has the latter, is like the same Person conversing with God on the serene top of it, and shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the Rays of <hi>anticipated</hi> Glory. So that this latter supposes the acquisition of the former, and consequently has all the <hi>Happiness</hi> retaining to the other, besides what it adds of its own. This is the last <hi>Stage</hi> of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49931:66"/>
                     <hi>Humane Perfection,</hi> the utmost <hi>round</hi> of the Ladder whereby we ascend to <hi>Heaven,</hi> one <hi>Step</hi> higher is Glory. Here then will I build my <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> for <hi>it is good to be here.</hi> Here will I set up my Pillar of Rest, here will I fix, for why should I travel on farther in pursuit of any greater <hi>Happiness,</hi> since Man in this Station is but a <hi>little lower than the Angels,</hi> one <hi>remove</hi> from <hi>Heaven.</hi> Here certainly is the greatest happiness, as well as Perfection at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable by Man in this State of imperfection. For since that Happiness which is absolutely perfect and compleat consists in the clear and intimate <hi>Vision</hi> and most ardent <hi>Love</hi> of God, hence we ought to take our Measures, and conclude that to be the greatest Happiness at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in this State, which is the greatest participation of the other. And that can be nothing else but the <hi>Ʋnitive</hi> way of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which consists of the <hi>Contemplation</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of God. I shall say something of each of these severally, and something of the <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> way of Religion, which is the result of both, and so shut up this Discourse.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Contemplation</hi> in general (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) we understand an application of the <hi>Ʋnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to some truth. But here in this place we take the word in a more peculiar sence, as it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49931:67"/>signifies an habitual, attentive, steddy applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or conversion of the Spirit to God and his Divine Perfections. Of this the Masters of <hi>Mystic Theology</hi> commonly make fifteen Degrees. The first is Intuition of Truth, the second is a Retirement of all the Vigour and Strength of the Faculties into the innermost parts of the Soul, the third is Spiritual Silence, the fourth is Rest, the fifth is Union, the sixth is the Hearing of the still Voice of God, the seventh is Spiritual Slumber, the eighth is Ecstacy, the ninth is Rapture, the tenth is the Corporeal Appearance of Christ and the Saints, the eleventh is the Imaginary Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Same, the twelfth is the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Vision of God, the thirteenth is the Vision of God in Obscurity, the fourteenth is an admirable Manifestation of God, the fifteenth is a clear and intuitive Vision of him, such as St. <hi>Austin</hi> and <hi>Tho. Aquinas</hi> attribute to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was rapt up into the third Heaven. Others of them reckon seven degrees only, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Taste, Desire, Satiety, Ebriety, Security, Tranquility, but the name of the seventh (they say) is known only to God.</p>
                  <p>I shall not stand to examine the <hi>Scale</hi> of this Division, perhaps there may be a kind
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49931:67"/>of a <hi>Pythagoric</hi> Suporstition in the number. But this I think I may affirm in general, that the Soul may be <hi>wound</hi> up to a most strange degree of <hi>Abstraction</hi> by a silent and steddy <hi>Contemplation</hi> of God. <hi>Plato</hi> desines <hi>Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a Solution and a Separation of the Soul from the Body. And some of the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer <hi>Platonists</hi> have been of Opinion, that 'tis possible for a Man by mere <hi>intention</hi> of thought not only to withdraw the Soul from all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the Senses, but even really to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate it from the Body, to <hi>untwist</hi> the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Frame, and by degrees to <hi>resolve</hi> himself into the State of the Dead. And thus the <hi>Jews</hi> express the manner of the Death of <hi>Moses,</hi> calling it <hi>Osculum Oris Dei, the Kiss of God</hi>'s <hi>Mouth.</hi> That is, that he breath'd out his Soul by the mere Strength and Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>Contemplation,</hi> and expired in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of his Maker. A Happy way of Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing! How ambitious should I be of such a conveyance, were it practicable? How passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately should I joyn with the Church in the Canticles? <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Let him Kiss me with the Kisses of his Mouth.</hi> Cant. 1 Ver. 2.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49931:68"/>
                  <p>But however this be determin'd, certain it is, that there are exceeding great Measures of <hi>Abstraction</hi> in <hi>Contemplation,</hi> so great, that sometimes whether a Man be in the Body or out of the Body, he himself can hardly tell. And consequently the Soul in these <hi>Praeludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums</hi> of Death, these <hi>Neighbourhoods</hi> of Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, must needs have <hi>brighter</hi> glimpses, and more <hi>Beatifick Ideas</hi> of God, than in a state void of these <hi>Elevations,</hi> and consequently must love him with greater Ardency. Which is the next thing I am to consider.</p>
                  <p>The love of God in general may be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered either as it is purely <hi>intellectual,</hi> or as it is a <hi>Passion.</hi> The first is, when the Soul, upon an apprehension of God as a good, dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, and agreeable Object, joyns her self to him by the Will. The latter is, when the motion of the Will is accompany'd with a sensible Commotion of the Spirits, and an estuation of the Blood. Some I know are of Opinion, that 'tis not possible for a man to be affected with this sensitive Love of God, which is a <hi>Passion,</hi> because there is nothing in God which falls under our ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and <hi>consequently</hi> (the imagination being the only Medium of conveyance) it cannot be propagated from the Intellectual
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49931:68"/>part to the Sensitive. Whereupon they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that none are capable of this sensitive passionate Love of God but Christians, who enjoy the <hi>Mystery</hi> of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they know God has condescended so far as to cloath himself with Flesh, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like one of us. But 'tis not all the <hi>Sophistry</hi> of the <hi>cold Logicians</hi> that shall work me out of the belief of what I feel and know, and rob me of the sweetest entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Life, the <hi>Passionate Love of God.</hi> Whatever some Men pretend, who are Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to all the assectionate heats of Religion, and therefore make their Philosophy a Plea for their indevotion, and extinguish all Holy Ardours with a <hi>Syllogism;</hi> yet I am firmly persuaded, that our love of God may be not only passionate, but even <hi>Wonderfully</hi> so, and <hi>exceeding the Love of Women.</hi> 'Tis an <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental</hi> and therefore <hi>undeniable</hi> Truth, that <hi>Passion</hi> is a great Instrument of <hi>Devotion,</hi> and accordingly we find, that Men of the most warm and pathetick <hi>Tempers</hi> and <hi>Amorous Complexions</hi> (Provided they have but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration enough withall to fix upon the right <hi>Object</hi>) prove the greatest <hi>Votaries</hi> in <hi>Religion.</hi> And upon this account it is, that to heighten our Love of God in our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49931:69"/>
                     <hi>Addresses,</hi> we <hi>endeavour</hi> to <hi>excite</hi> our Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions by <hi>Music,</hi> which would be to as little purpose as the <hi>Fanatic</hi> thinks 'tis, if there were not such a thing as the <hi>Passionate Love of God.</hi> But then as to the <hi>Objection,</hi> I <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer</hi> with the <hi>excellent Descartes,</hi> that although in God who is the <hi>Object</hi> of our <hi>Love,</hi> we can <hi>imagine</hi> nothing, yet we can <hi>imagine</hi> that our Love, which consists in this, that we would unite our <hi>selves</hi> to the <hi>Object</hi> beloved, and consider our <hi>selves</hi> as it were a part of it. And the sole <hi>Idea</hi> of this very Conjunction is enough to stir up a heat about the Heart, and so kindle a very <hi>vehement Passion.</hi> To which I add, that although the <hi>Beauty</hi> or <hi>Amiableness</hi> of God be not the same with that which we see in <hi>Corporeal Beings,</hi> and <hi>consequently</hi> cannot <hi>directly</hi> fall within the <hi>Sphere</hi> of the imagination, yet it is something <hi>Analogous</hi> to it, and that very <hi>Analogy</hi> is enough to <hi>excite</hi> a <hi>Passion.</hi> And this I think sufficient to warrant my general division of the Love of God into <hi>Intellectual</hi> and <hi>Sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But there is a more <hi>peculiar Acceptation</hi> of the <hi>Love</hi> of God proper to this place. And it is that which we call <hi>Seraphic.</hi> By which I understand in short, that Love of God which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49931:69"/>is the <hi>effect</hi> of an intense <hi>Contemplation</hi> of him. This differs not from the other in kind, but only in <hi>degree,</hi> and that it does <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,</hi> in as much as the thoughtful <hi>Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative</hi> Man (as I hinted before) has <hi>clearer Perceptions</hi> and <hi>livelier Impressions</hi> of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Beauty,</hi> the lovely <hi>Attributes</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> of God, than he whose Soul is more deeply <hi>set</hi> in the <hi>Flesh,</hi> and lies groveling in the <hi>bottom</hi> of the <hi>Dungeon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the nature of this <hi>Seraphic Love</hi> may be the better understood, I shall consider how many <hi>degrees there</hi> may be in the <hi>Love</hi> of God. And I think the Computation of <hi>Bellarmin, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis, cap.</hi> 2. is <hi>accurate</hi> enough. He makes four. The first is to <hi>love</hi> God proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to <hi>his Loveliness,</hi> that is, with an <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Love;</hi> and this <hi>degree</hi> is peculiar to God himself. The second is to Love him, not proportionably to his <hi>Loveliness,</hi> but to the utmost Capacity of a <hi>Creature,</hi> and this <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> is peculiar to Saints and Angels in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> The third is to love him not propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably to his <hi>Loveliness,</hi> nor to the utmost capacity of a <hi>Creature,</hi> absolutely consider'd, but to the utmost capacity of a <hi>Mortal Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49931:70"/>in this Life. And this (he says) is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the <hi>Religious.</hi> The fourth is to love him not proportionably to his <hi>Loveliness,</hi> nor to the utmost capacity of a <hi>Creature,</hi> consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd either absolutely or with respect to this <hi>Life,</hi> but only so as to love nothing equally with him or above him. That is, not to do any thing contrary to the <hi>Divine Love.</hi> And this is absolute indispensable duty, less than which will not qualify us for the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of God hereafter.</p>
                  <p>Now this <hi>Seraphic Love</hi> which we here discourse of is in the third degree: When a Man, after many <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>Abstraction</hi> from the <hi>Animal</hi> Life, many a profound and sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Meditation upon the <hi>Excellencies</hi> of God, sees such a vast <hi>Ocean</hi> of <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Perfection</hi> in him, that he loves him to the utmost <hi>stretch</hi> of his Power; <hi>When he sits under his shadow with great delight, and his fruit is sweet to his Tast.</hi> Cant. 2.3. When he <hi>Consecrates</hi> and <hi>Devotes</hi> himself wholly to him, and has no Passion for Inferiour <hi>Objects.</hi> When he is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vished with the <hi>delights</hi> of his <hi>Service,</hi> and breaths out some of his Soul to him in every Prayer. When he is delighted with <hi>Anthems</hi> of Praise and Adoration more than with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49931:70"/>
                     <hi>Marrow and Fatness,</hi> and <hi>Feasts</hi> upon <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiah.</hi> When he melts in a <hi>Calenture of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion,</hi> and his <hi>Soul breaketh out with fervent Desire.</hi> Psal. 119. When the one thing he <hi>delights</hi> in is to converse with God in the <hi>Beauty</hi> of <hi>Holiness,</hi> and the one thing he <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires to see him as he is in</hi> Heaven. This is <hi>Seraphic</hi> Love, and this with <hi>Contemplation</hi> makes up that which the <hi>Mystic</hi> Divines stile the <hi>Ʋnitive</hi> way of Religion: It is called so because it Unites us to God in the most <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent manner</hi> that we are capable of in this Life. By Union here I do not understand that which is <hi>local</hi> or <hi>presential,</hi> because I consider God as <hi>Omnipresent.</hi> Neither do I mean a Union of Grace (as they call it) whereby we are <hi>reconciled</hi> to God, or a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Charity, whereof it is said, <hi>he that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in love, dwelleth in God and God in him.</hi> Jo. 4.16. The first of these being as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the inanimate things as to the most <hi>Extasi'd</hi> Soul upon Earth. And the two last being common to all good men, who indeed love God, but yet want the <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>Contemplation</hi> and the <hi>Mystic</hi> Union. The Union then which I here speak of, is that which is between the <hi>Faculty</hi> and <hi>the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49931:71"/>Which consists in some Habitude or Operation of one toward the <hi>other.</hi> The <hi>Faculties here</hi> are the <hi>Ʋnderstanding</hi> and <hi>Will, the Object</hi> God, and the <hi>Operations Contemplation</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> The result of <hi>which</hi> two is the <hi>Mystic Ʋnion.</hi> Which, according to his <hi>complex</hi> Notion of it that I <hi>have here</hi> delivered,
<note place="margin">The great Exemplar, <hi>pag.</hi> 60.</note> is thus most admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably represented by the excellent Bishop <hi>Taylour. It is</hi> (says he) <hi>a Prayer of quietness and silence, and a Meditation extraordinary, a Discourse with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out variety, a Vision and Intuition of Divine Excellencies, an immediate entry into an Orb of light, and a resolution of all our Faculties into Sweetness, Affections, and Starings upon the Divine Beauty. And is carried on to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasies, Raptures, Suspensions, Elevations, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions and Apprehensions beatifical.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I make no doubt but that many an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Pious Soul arrives to the heavenly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> who is not fed with this <hi>Manna</hi> in the <hi>Wilderness.</hi> But though every one must not expect these <hi>Antepasts</hi> of Felicity that is vertuous, yet none else must. <hi>Paradise</hi> was never open but to a State of <hi>Innocence.</hi> But neither is that enough. No, this Mount of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49931:71"/>God's Presence is fenced not only from the <hi>profane,</hi> but also from the <hi>moderately</hi> vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. 'Tis the Priviledge of Angelical Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, and the Reward of <hi>eminent</hi> Piety and an excellent Religion, to be admitted to these <hi>Divine Repasts,</hi> these Feasts of <hi>love.</hi> And here I place the greatest Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness attainable by Man in this Life, as being the nearest Approach to the State of the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed above, the <hi>onter Court</hi> of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>These (Sir) are my thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Happiness. I might have <hi>spun</hi> them out into a greater length, but I think a little Plot of ground <hi>thick-sown</hi> is better than a great Field which for the most part of it lies Fallow. I have endeavour'd to deliver my Notions with as much Perspicuity and in as good Method as I could, and so to answer all the ends of <hi>Copiousness,</hi> with the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a shorter Cut. If I appear singular in any of my Notions, 'tis not out of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious affectation of Novelty, but because in the composing of this discourse (the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of a few broken hours in a Garden) I consulted more my own experimental No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices of things and private <hi>Reflections</hi> than the Writings of others. So that if sometimes I
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49931:72"/>happen to be in the Road, and sometimes in a way by my self, 'tis no wonder. I affect neither the one nor the other, but write as I think. Which as I do at other times, so more especially when I subscribe my self</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     <signed>Yours most affectionately,<hi> J. N.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>All-Souls Colledge</hi>
                        <date>Apr. 18. 1683.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49931:72"/>
                  <head>A Letter of Resolution concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing some Passages in the sore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Treatise, to the same Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE kind Entertainment which you gave my <hi>Idea of Happiness,</hi> does not only <hi>incourage,</hi> but <hi>oblige</hi> me to endeavour the satisfaction of that Scruple, which the Perusal of it has occasion'd. I cannot but highly commend your <hi>searching</hi> Curiosity, in desiring farther satisfaction concerning a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of so sublime and excellent a Nature (for the Tree of Paradise is <hi>good for food, pleasant to the Eye, and a Tree to be desired to make one wise</hi>) tho you must give me leave to wonder that you would not <hi>inquire</hi> at a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Oracle.</hi> But since you are <hi>pleas'd</hi> to be of the Opinion, that few have made this Subject so <hi>familiar</hi> to their Meditation as I have, I cannot with any pretence decline your Request, tho perhaps by my perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49931:73"/>it I shall work you into a contrary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion.</p>
                  <p>Sir, You say you should like my Notion concerning the <hi>reality</hi> of that which is usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd <hi>Imaginary Happiness,</hi> that is, (as you well explain both your own and my meaning) that although the <hi>Object</hi> may be an <hi>Imaginary Good,</hi> yet the <hi>Happiness</hi> which consists in the Fruition of that Object, will not be <hi>Imaginary too,</hi> but <hi>real,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that 'tis impossible for a man to <hi>seem</hi> to himself to be happy, and not to <hi>be really</hi> so, all Happiness consisting in <hi>Opinion.</hi> This Notion, you say, you should like rarely well, could you free your self from one dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty which it engages you upon; <hi>(viz.)</hi> That hereafter, in the state of Glory, either one Saint shall think himself as happy as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, or not; if not, this must needs occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Envy or Discontent, but if one shall think himself as happy as another, then, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> that <hi>Opinion</hi> is the <hi>Measure of Happiness,</hi> 'twill follow that he will really be so; and this brings in <hi>Equality</hi> of Happiness, which you look upon (and I think justly too) as another absurdity.</p>
                  <p>I confess, Sir, this Argument is pretty subtle and surprizing, but I conceive the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49931:73"/>Knots of it may be untied by this Answer. First, it may be justly question'd, whether the first part of your <hi>Dilemma</hi> be necessarily attended with the appendant absurdity. 'Tis true indeed, not to think ones self as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as another, is the Spring of Envy or Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content among Men in this World, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be the <hi>genuin</hi> and <hi>constant</hi> effect of that Consideration, or whether it ought not rather to be ascribed to the present Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Imperfections of Human Nature, may admit Dispute. But in case this absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity does inseparably cleave to the first part, then I betake my self to the latter, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that in Heaven one Saint shall think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self as happy as another. Then, according to my own Notion <hi>(say you)</hi> it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that he <hi>is really</hi> so. No, I deny the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence, the invalidity of which will plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear by distinguishing the ambiguity of the <hi>Phrase.</hi> For this Expression, <hi>One Saint thinks himself as happy as another,</hi> may be taken in a double sense, either that he thinks himself as happy as he himself thinks that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or that he thinks himself as happy as that other thinks himself. I grant, should one Saint think himself as happy as another in this latter sense of the Phrase, he would,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49931:74"/>according to my <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> really be so; so that this would bring in equality. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this Sense I deny the Proposition, and that without the least danger of splitting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the first absurdity. But for the former Sense, <hi>that</hi> has no such <hi>levelling</hi> quality, for to say that I think my self as happy as I think another, amounts to no more than this, that in my apprehension another does not exceed me in Happiness: But tho he does not in <hi>my apprehension,</hi> yet he may in <hi>reality,</hi> for tho my Opinion gives measures to my <hi>own</hi> Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, yet it does not to <hi>another</hi> Mans. So that one Saint may be said to think himself as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as another in the former sense, without equalling the Happiness of the Blessed, tho, I confess, I should much rather adhere to the contrary proposition, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that <hi>one shall not think himself as happy as another,</hi> in case such an Opinion be not necessarily attended with <hi>Envy</hi> or <hi>Discontent.</hi> Because it seems unreasonable to make them ignorant of the degrees of one anothers Bliss, unless that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance be necessarily required to prevent the alledg'd absurdities. But I <hi>determin</hi> nothing in this point, my business was only to break the force of your <hi>Dilemma,</hi> and to shew that my Notion does not involve you in the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49931:74"/>supposed. This, Sir, is all that I think necessary to say to a Person of your appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, and therefore I end these nice Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations with this profitable reflection, that altho the <hi>Notion</hi> of Happiness be <hi>intricate</hi> and <hi>obscure,</hi> yet the <hi>means</hi> of attaining it are <hi>plain,</hi> and therefore 'twould be most advisa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble both for you and me <hi>chiefly</hi> to apply our selves to the <hi>latter here,</hi> and we shall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the <hi>former</hi> with the best sort of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that of <hi>Experience, hereafter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours <hi>J. N.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49931:75"/>
                  <head>Another Letter to the same Person, concerning the true Notion of <hi>Plato</hi>'s <hi>Ideas,</hi> and of <hi>Platonic Love.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WEre I not as well acquainted with your singular <hi>modesty,</hi> as I am with your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual</hi> accomplishments, I should readily conclude, that your directing your inquiries to <hi>me</hi> proceeded not so much from a Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity to <hi>improve</hi> your <hi>own</hi> Knowledge, as to <hi>try mine.</hi> But when I consider that you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of nothing so much as of your own Worth and Abilities, I begin to think it possible that you may propose these <hi>Questions</hi> even to <hi>me</hi> out of a desire to be <hi>inform'd.</hi> Which way so ever it is, I acknowledge my self to be obliged to you for affording me an opportunity of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you, especially in such an Instance, where I cannot gratify your Request with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>humouring</hi> my own <hi>Genius</hi> at the same time. For indeed to my apprehension, there
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49931:75"/>is not a finer or more Sublime piece of Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation in all <hi>Plato</hi>'s <hi>Philosophy,</hi> than that of his <hi>Ideas</hi> and that of his <hi>Love,</hi> tho it has undergon the same hard Fate with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excellent <hi>Theories,</hi> first, to be either <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly misunderstood,</hi> or <hi>malitiously misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented,</hi> and then <hi>popularly</hi> vilify'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry'd.</p>
                  <p>To do right therefore to the name of this great Man, as well as to satisfy your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, I shall first <hi>propose</hi> the general mistake, and then <hi>rectify</hi> it, first present you with the <hi>sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd</hi> Opinion of <hi>Plato,</hi> and then with the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>genuin</hi> one. I begin with his <hi>Ideas,</hi> by which 'tis taken for granted by the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> of Writers, especially those of the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripatetic Order,</hi> that he understood <hi>universal</hi> Natures or abstract Essences subsisting eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by themselves, Separate both from the mind of God and all singular Beings, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which, as so many <hi>patterns,</hi> all Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are form'd. As for instance, that a Bull, not this or that <hi>in</hi> particular, but a <hi>universal</hi> Bull, or a Bull in general, should exist by it self eternally, according to which all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Bulls were made. Sir, I suppose you can hardly forbear smiling at the odness of the Conceit, but as ridiculous as you may
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49931:76"/>think it, 'tis said to be maintained by no less a Man than <hi>Plato,</hi> and has been thought of that <hi>moment</hi> too, that <hi>Multitudes</hi> of great Men have set themselves very <hi>seriously</hi> to confute it as a dangerous Heresy, and have opposed it with as much <hi>zeal</hi> as ever St. <hi>Austin</hi> did the <hi>Manichees</hi> or the <hi>Pelagians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now, that this Opinion was not only for its Absurdity and Contradictiousness unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the contemplative and refin'd Spirit of <hi>Plato;</hi> but was also apparently none of his, I dare say any capable Person will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that shall heedfully and impartially <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin</hi> and <hi>compare</hi> the Works of <hi>Plato;</hi> And this <hi>Aristotle</hi> himself must needs have known (he having been his constant Auditour for twenty years together) but only he wanted a Shadow to fight with, and so father'd this monstrous Opinion upon his Master. And of this disingenuity of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> together with other abuses, <hi>Plato</hi> himself complain'd, while alive, in these words; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as is recorded by <hi>Laertius</hi> in the Life of <hi>Aristotle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now, that the grossness of this Abuse may the more fully appear, I will in the next place present you with another Sense of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>'s
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49931:76"/>
                     <hi>Ideas,</hi> and such as by a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary acquaintance with his Works, I know to be the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>genuin</hi> one. Know then that <hi>Plato</hi> considering the World as an effect of an <hi>intellectual</hi> Agent, and that in the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of all other <hi>Artificers</hi> or rational <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients</hi> there must be some form in the Mind of the <hi>Artificer</hi> presupposed to the Work (for otherwise what difference will there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>fortuitous</hi> effect and an <hi>intended</hi> one, and how comes the effect to be of <hi>this</hi> Species rather than <hi>another?</hi>) thought it necessary to suppose <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Eternal Forms, Models or Patterns, of all the Species of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Nature existing in the Mind of God. And these he calls <hi>Ideas.</hi> I say existing in the Mind of God, for there is not the least Intimation in all <hi>Plato</hi>'s Works of any such <hi>Ideas</hi> existing <hi>separately</hi> from the Divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, nor do the great Masters of <hi>Platonic Philosophy, Plotinus, Porphyrius, Procles,</hi> or any other that I know of make mention of any such <hi>Spectres</hi> and <hi>Ghosts</hi> of Entity. No, this Monster was hatch'd in <hi>Aristotle</hi>'s Brain, and I believe did never enter <hi>Plato</hi>'s Head so much as in a Dream. For he is not only si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent about it, but does in several places ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly assert the contrary; Particularly in his <hi>Timaeus,</hi> where, of set purpose, he describes the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49931:77"/>
                     <hi>Origin</hi> of the World, he says that God made the World according to that Pattern or <hi>Idea</hi> which he had in his Mind. The same you will find more amply confirm'd in his <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias,</hi> his <hi>Parmenides,</hi> and his sixth Book of <hi>Repub.</hi> and many other places. And these <hi>Ideas</hi> he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the first Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibles,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the Measures of the things that are,</hi> implying, that as all things were form'd according to these <hi>specifical</hi> Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms; so their truth must be measur'd from their Conformity to them. And in this Sense must be taken that Common Axiom of the Schools, that <hi>the Truth of a thing is its Conformity with the Divine Intellect,</hi> for it is in no other Sense Intelligible, as you will discern in the Process.</p>
                  <p>But now, lest you should imagine, that this <hi>Platonic Hypothesis</hi> of <hi>Ideas</hi> existing in the Divine Mind should ill comport with the Simplicity of God, or clash with that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Doctrin of the Schools, <hi>Nihil est in Deo quod non sit deus,</hi> (which is another ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of the <hi>Antiplatonists</hi>) you are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand that <hi>Plato</hi> by his <hi>Ideas</hi> does not mean any <hi>real</hi> Essence <hi>distinct</hi> from the Divine Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, but only the Divine Essence it self with this <hi>Connotation,</hi> as it is variously imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table or participable by created Beings, and consequently, according to the <hi>multifarious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49931:77"/>of this imitability, so are the <hi>possibilities</hi> of Being. Which is as fine a Notion as was ever framed by the Mind of Man, and that it is his, you will find, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult his <hi>Parmenides.</hi> And this will serve to help us out with another difficulty, for whereas <hi>Plato</hi> makes his <hi>Divine Ideas</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>exemplary</hi> causes of things, but also (which is a consequent to the former) the measure of their Truth, this may seem to fall in with their Opinion who make all <hi>Truth</hi> dependent upon the Speculative understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, that is, that God does not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand a thing so because it is so in its own Nature, but that a thing is therefore so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God is <hi>pleas'd</hi> so to understand it. Which is an Opinion full of mischief and absurdity, as you may see compendiously, and yet evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently demonstrated, in Dr. <hi>Rust</hi>'s little <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course</hi> of <hi>Truth.</hi> Now for the clearing this Difficulty, 'tis to be observed, that the Essence of God, according to <hi>Plato,</hi> is distinguished into <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>Counterpart</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in English is <hi>Conceptive</hi> and <hi>Exhibitive.</hi> By the Mind of God <hi>Exhibitive</hi> is meant the Essence of God as thus or thus imitable or participable by any Creature, and this is the same with an <hi>Idea.</hi> By the Mind of God <hi>Conceptive</hi> is meant a reflex act of God's Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49931:78"/>upon his own Essence as <hi>exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> or as thus and thus imitable. Now if you consider the Divine Understanding as <hi>Conceptive</hi> or <hi>Speculative,</hi> it does not <hi>make</hi> its Object but suppose it, (as all <hi>Speculative</hi> Understanding does) neither is the Truth of the Object to be measured from its Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with <hi>that,</hi> but the Truth of <hi>that</hi> from its Conformity with its Object. But if you consider the Divine Understanding as <hi>Exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitive,</hi> then its Truth does not depend upon its Conformity with the Nature of things, but on the contrary, the Truth of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things depends upon its Conformity with it. For the Divine Essence is not thus or thus imitable, because such and such things are in being, but such and such things are in being, because the Divine Essence is thus and thus imitable, for had not the Divine Essence been thus imitable, such and such Beings would not have been <hi>possible.</hi> And thus is <hi>Plato</hi> to be understood when he founds the Truth of things upon their Conformity with the <hi>Divine Ideas,</hi> and thus must the Schools mean too by that foremention'd <hi>Axiom</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Transcendental Truth,</hi> if they will speak Sense, as I noted above.</p>
                  <p>And now, Sir, from <hi>Plato</hi>'s Ideas thus <hi>ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably</hi> set forth, the <hi>Transition</hi> methinks is very
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49931:78"/>natural to <hi>Love.</hi> And concerning this I shall account in the same Method, first, by point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the popular Misapprehensions about it, and then by exhibiting a true Notion of it. <hi>Platonick Love</hi> is a thing in every bodies Mouth, but I find scarce any that think or speak accurately of it. The mistakes which I observe are chiefly these. Some of the gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser Understanders suppose that <hi>Plato</hi> by his <hi>Love</hi> meant <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>Males,</hi> but the Occasion of this Conceit was from a pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage in his <hi>Convivium,</hi> where he brings in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristophanes</hi> speaking favourably that way. But he that shall from hence conclude <hi>Plato</hi> a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute</hi> to that vile Passion, may as well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a <hi>Dramatic</hi> Poet to be an <hi>Atheist</hi> or a <hi>Whore-master,</hi> because he represents those of that Character. But that Divine <hi>Plato</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothing less than to countenance any such thing, is evident from the whole scope and purport of that <hi>Dialogue,</hi> and from other places where he expresly condemns it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects it with great abhorrence; particularly in the first of his <hi>de legibus,</hi> where he calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>an unnatural attempt.</hi> Others by <hi>Platonic Love</hi> understand the Love of <hi>Souls,</hi> and this indeed has something of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49931:79"/>truth in it, only it is much too narrow and particular.</p>
                  <p>Others take <hi>Platonic Love</hi> to be a desire of imprinting any excellency, whether moral or intellectual, in the Minds of beautiful young men by Instruction, and so likewise of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your own Perfections reflected from the Mind of another, mix'd <hi>with</hi> and recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>by</hi> the Beauty of the Body. According to the usual saying, <hi>Gratior è Pulchro, &amp;c.</hi> And thus <hi>Socrates</hi> was said to love his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Pupils <hi>Phaedrus</hi> and <hi>Alcibiades.</hi> Others measure the Nature of <hi>Platonic Love,</hi> not from the <hi>Object</hi> (to which they suppose it indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent) but from the <hi>manner</hi> of the <hi>Act.</hi> And according to these, that man is said to love <hi>Platonically,</hi> that does <hi>Casso delectamine amare,</hi> love at a distance, that never designs a <hi>close</hi> fruition of the Object what ever it be, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sensual or Intellectual, but chooses to dwell in the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> pleasing himself with remote Prospects, and makes a <hi>Mistriss</hi> of his own <hi>Desire.</hi> And this is the receiv'd Notion, and that which People generally mean when they talk of <hi>Platonic Love.</hi> But this too is far enough from the right, for tho <hi>Platonic love</hi> does not aim at the fruition of sensual Objects, yet it designs the fruition of its own Object as much as any other Love does. That
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49931:79"/>therefore which distinguishes <hi>Platonick love,</hi> is not the <hi>manner</hi> of the act above-mention'd, but the peculiarity of the <hi>Object.</hi> And what that is must be collected from the Design of <hi>Plato</hi> in that <hi>Dialogue,</hi> where he treats pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely of it, his <hi>Convivium.</hi> Which is brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to shew the manner of the Souls ascent to God by love. For <hi>Plato</hi> makes the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Man to consist in the Contemplation and Love of God, whom he calls the <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Beauty.</hi> But now because this <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Beauty</hi> (God) is of too sublime and refined excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency to be immediately fastned upon by our Love, he recommends to us <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>a Method of Ascent,</hi> which is from loving the Beauty we see in Bodies, to pass on to the Love of the Beauty of the Soul, from the Beauty of the Soul to the Beauty of Vertue, and last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Beauty of Vertue, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to the immense <hi>Ocean of Beauty, &amp;c.</hi> For so have I observ'd a tender Infants Eye not enduring to gaze directly upon the too powerful Excellence of the <hi>Meridian</hi> Sun, chuse to entertain it self with the abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of corrected and reflected Light, and take up with the <hi>feebler</hi> refreshments of lesser Beauties for a while, till at length the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49931:80"/>grows more confirm'd, and dares encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sun in his Strength. And these are the <hi>Steps</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary.</hi> So that <hi>Platonic Love</hi> is the Love of Beauty abstracted from all sensual Applications, and desire of corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral contract, as it leads us on to the Love of the first original Beauty, God; or more plainly thus, The Ascent of the Soul to the Love of the <hi>Divine</hi> Beauty, by the Love of <hi>abstracted</hi> Beauty in Bodies. This Love of abstracted Beauty in Bodies he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Celestial Love,</hi> in opposition to that which he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which is the same with that Passion commonly fignifi'd by the name of Love, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a desire of corporal contact arising from the sight of Beauty. This last indeed is a very vile, brutish, unmanly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and such as considering the vileness of our Bodies, one would think a man could never be charm'd into without the <hi>Magic</hi> of a <hi>Love-potion.</hi> But the former is an Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Affection, for certainly Beauty is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine thing; It is (as the <hi>Platonic</hi> Author says of Wisdom) <hi>the pure Influence flowing from the Glory of the Almighty, and the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Everlasting Light:</hi> or in <hi>Plato</hi>'s own Words, <hi>A Ray of God.</hi> And therefore the Love of abstract Beauty must needs be a very
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49931:80"/>generous and divine Affection. Sir, I could be more large in my account, but I consider <hi>what</hi> 'tis I write, and to <hi>whom,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I think it high time to remit you to your own Thoughts, some of which I hope will be, that <hi>I am in a very</hi> eminent degree of Friendship,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours <hi>J. Norris.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Study in All-Souls Colledge.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="authors_note">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:81"/>
                  <head>Advertisement of the Authour.</head>
                  <p>WHEREAS it has been given out by seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and is by many still believed, that a certain Book intituled <hi>Haec Et Hic,</hi> was written by me, I do here publickly disown it. And to those that will not take my word for it, I have this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly farther to say, that if they are <hi>tolerable</hi> Judges of Sense, or have any thing of <hi>taste</hi> in distinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stiles, they will find upon Comparison, that there is not a Line in that Book like any <hi>Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of mine. But if not, their good Opinion will be <hi>over-bought</hi> at the <hi>Expence</hi> of a <hi>Postscript.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>PAge 29. for <hi>decipere</hi> read <hi>desipere.</hi> Pag. 30. for <hi>quantum</hi> read <hi>quantam.</hi> Pag, 31. for <hi>quot</hi> read <hi>quod,</hi> Pag. 32. for <hi>janique</hi> read <hi>jamque.</hi> ibid. for <hi>Corde</hi> read <hi>Corda.</hi> Pag. 45. for learn'd read learn't. Pag. 46. for learn'd read learn't.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49931:81"/>
                  <head>Books set forth by the Author of these Poems and Discourses. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>EFFIGIES Amoris,</hi> or the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Love unveil'd, in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, twelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Meditation of Life and Death, out of the learned <hi>Eusebius,</hi> in English, octavo.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Hierocles</hi> upon the Golden Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> in English, octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A Tract against the absolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Reprobation, Latin, octavo.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>